[
    {
        "id": 1,
        "Question": "The first National Highway of India, NH 1 connects New Delhi to which town in India?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sri- Nagar",
            "b) Attari",
            "c) Kolkata",
            "d) Rajkot"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The first National Highway of India, NH 1 connects New Delhi to Attari, a town in Punjab, near the India-Pakistan border. Old NH 1 was part of Grand Trunk Road, GT Road.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 2,
        "Question": "The Golden Quadrilateral connects which four major cities in India?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Delhi, Mumbai, Chennai and Kolkata",
            "b) Delhi, Mumbai, Chennai and Guwahati",
            "c) Delhi, Surat, Mumbai and Bangalore",
            "d) Surat, Mumbai, Bangalore and Kolkata"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Golden Quadrilateral connects the four major cities Delhi, Mumbai, Chennai and Kolkata. It was a project under the National Highway Development Program (NHDP).\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 3,
        "Question": "Which programme was introduced to improve road connectivity in North-East India?",
        "Options": [
            "a) National Highways Authority of India",
            "b) Border Roads Development Board",
            "c) Special Accelerated Road Development Programme",
            "d) Setu Bharatam"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Indian railways are the largest employer in the world. It has a workforce of 14 lakhs employees according to Indian Railways Annual Report and Accounts 2006-07.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 4,
        "Question": "The Motor Vehicle Act was passed by the Parliament of India in the year _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1988",
            "b) 1942",
            "c) 1995",
            "d) 2000"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Special Accelerated Road Development Programme (SARD) was Introduced in North-East India to improve road connectivity with the state capital, district headquarters and remote places in the region. National Highways Authority of India is responsible for management on National Highways in India. Border Road Development Board developed and maintains road connectivity in India’s border. Setu Bharatam was introduced in 2016 to make all national highways free of railway crossings.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 5,
        "Question": "The longest bridge in India, Dhola-Sadia bridge spans over which river?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lohit river",
            "b) Dihing River",
            "c) Manas River",
            "d) Sankosh river"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Motor Vehicle Act was passed by the Parliament of India in the year 1988. Under this act, it is mandatory for a driver to have a valid driving license and motor vehicles to have a certificate of registration.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 6,
        "Question": "Who was the chairman of the Indian Road development committee, 1927?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Yogendra Narain",
            "b) M.R.Jayakar",
            "c) Lt. Gen.Harpal Singh",
            "d) R. K. Chaturvedi"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The longest bridge in India, Dhola-Sadia bridge, also known as Bhupen Hazarika Setu spans over Lohit river which is a major tributary of the Brahmaputra river.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 7,
        "Question": "What is the main function of the Central Road Research Institute (1951)?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Research on road construction and to provide consultation services for the state government",
            "b) Develop and maintain roads in the institute",
            "c) Planning of various road maintenance programmes",
            "d) To provide the standards and the specifications for the road construction in the country"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The chairman of Indian Road development committee, 1927 also known as Jayakar Committee was M.R.Jayakar. Yogendra Narain was the first Chairman of NHAI in 1988. Lt. Gen.Harpal Singh is the Director General of Border Roads Organisation, BRO.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 8,
        "Question": "Who launched the National Green Highway Program?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ministry of Transport and NHAI",
            "b) Border Roads Organisation",
            "c) Public Works Department",
            "d) Indian Road Development Committee"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The main function of Central Road Research Institute (1951) is to do research on road construction and to provide consultation services for the state government. IRC is responsible for various planning and standards and specifications for road constructions in the country.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 9,
        "Question": "When was the Inland Waterways Authority of India established?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1986",
            "b) 1942",
            "c) 1995",
            "d) 1982"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: National Green Highway Program was launched by Ministry of Transport and NHAI on 29 September 2015 to develop green corridors along National Highways for a sustainable environment. It also aims to generate one lakh employment in the plantation sector.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 10,
        "Question": "The first train journey in India was made between which two cities?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bombay and Nashik",
            "b) Bombay and Thane",
            "c) Nagpur and Pune",
            "d) Nashik and Dadar"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Indian Railways was nationalised in the year 1950 and a year after that Indian Railway was formed, under the Ministry of Railways. Railway nationalization was initiated in order to take railway assets into public ownership.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 11,
        "Question": "Which one of the four options given below does not belong to Nagpur Plan of 1943?",
        "Options": [
            "a) State Highways",
            "b) District roads",
            "c) National Highways",
            "d) Expressways"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Inland Waterways Authority of India (IWAI) was set up on 27th October 1986. It was constituted under NHAI Act-1985 by Parliament of India. Its main aim was to develop and regulate inland waterways for shipping and navigation.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 12,
        "Question": "Why was the Central Road Fund (CRF) created?",
        "Options": [
            "a) To impose a tax on the consumption of Petrol and Diesel",
            "b) To impose tolls on bridges",
            "c) To collect fund from various national organisations",
            "d) To Impose a tax on vehicle buyers"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The first train journey in India was made between Bombay and Thane on 16 April 1853. The train was 14 carriage long and was drawn by 3 locomotives named Sultan, Sindh and Sahib.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 13,
        "Question": "Which scheme in India has 50 percent of the cess levied on High-Speed Diesel (HSD) earmarked to fund it?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Central Road Fund (CRF)",
            "b) Pradhan Mantri Gram Sadak Yojana (PMGSY)",
            "c) Border Roads Development Organisation (BRO)",
            "d) National Bank for Agriculture and Rural Development (NABARD)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Nagpur plan of 1943 included National Highways, State Highways, District roads and village roads.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 14,
        "Question": "Canal Transport comes under which mode of transportation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Land Transport",
            "b) Water transport",
            "c) Air transport",
            "d) Underground transport"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Canal Transport comes under water mode of transportation. Canals are manmade waterways and its function is to navigate and provide water for irrigation. It comes under the subcategory of Inland water transport.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 15,
        "Question": "Which is the cheapest mode of transportation in India?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Air transport",
            "b) Land transport",
            "c) Water transport",
            "d) Railway"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Water transport is the oldest and cheapest mode of transportation. It doesn’t require a huge amount of capital for construction, unlike railways and roadways.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 16,
        "Question": "Which was the first commercial airport in India?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mumbai-Juhu Airport",
            "b) Indira Gandhi International Airport, New Delhi",
            "c) Bengaluru International Airport, Bengaluru",
            "d) Chhatrapati Shivaji International Airport, Mumbai"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It is true that Kerala has the highest density of roads in the country. It is followed by Tripura and West Bengal.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 17,
        "Question": "Which is the oldest port in India?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Kandla Port",
            "b) Kamajhar Port",
            "c) Lothal Port",
            "d) Morgugao Port"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Mumbai-Juhu Airport in Juhu was the first civil airport in India. It was founded in the year 1928 as the as India’s first civil aviation airport. It also served as a primary airport during World War II.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 18,
        "Question": "Which of the following authority responsible for managing shipping and trade through a commercial seaport?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Port Trust Board",
            "b) Inland Waterways Authority of India (IWAI)",
            "c) Port Authority of India",
            "d) Port Association of India"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Lothal Port is the oldest port in India. It dates back to 3800 BCE. It was the port of the ancient city of Lothal which is now located in the Bhal region of Gujarat. It was discovered in the year 1954 and is nominated as a UNESCO World Heritage Site.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 19,
        "Question": "Which National Waterway (NW) runs from Haldia to Prayagraj?",
        "Options": [
            "a) NW-1",
            "b) NW-2",
            "c) NW-3",
            "d) NW-4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Port Trust Board manages shipping and trade through a commercial seaport while Inland Waterways Authority of India (IWAI) deals with the responsibility of development and regulation of inland waterways for shipping and navigation.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 20,
        "Question": "In how many zones is the rail network divided into?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 20",
            "b) 17",
            "c) 15",
            "d) 10"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: NW-1 or Ganga-Bhagirathi-Hooghly river system runs from Haldi at the south end and Prayagraj at the north. NW-2 or Sadiya-Dhubri stretch of the Brahmaputra river. NW-3, Kottapuram-Kollam stretch of the West Coast Canal.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 21,
        "Question": "Where is the zone headquarter for the South Central Railway?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Secunderabad",
            "b) Hyderabad",
            "c) Vijayawada",
            "d) Nanded"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The rail network is divided into 17 zones in India. The zones are then divided into divisions. There are total of 68 divisions. Konkan Railways is the newest zone added and it’s controlled by Railway Board and Railway Ministry.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 22,
        "Question": "Which city given below doesn’t have metro rail connectivity? (As on year 2019)",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bangalore",
            "b) Delhi",
            "c) Chennai",
            "d) Thiruvananthapuram"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The zone headquarters for the South Central Railway zone is Secunderabad. Secunderabad, Hyderabad Vijayawada, Guntakal, Guntur and Nanded are the railway divisions of the South Central Railway zone.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 23,
        "Question": "The first bus service in India was started in the year _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1926",
            "b) 1942",
            "c) 1966",
            "d) 1988"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Thiruvananthapuram, Kerala doesn’t have metro rail connectivity yet. But a proposed rapid transit system, Trivandrum Metro will start its operation in 2025.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 24,
        "Question": "The Konkan rail line was fully operational in the year _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2000",
            "b) 1998",
            "c) 1996",
            "d) 1988"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The first bus service in India was started in the year 1926 on 15th July. It ran between Afghan Church and Crawford Market, Mumbai.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 25,
        "Question": "The first line of Delhi Metro was inaugurated on _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) December 24, 2002",
            "b) December 22, 2002",
            "c) November 22, 2002",
            "d) November 24, 2002"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The Konkan rail line was fully operational on Roha to Mangalore section in the year 1998.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 26,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not the function of Transportation organization?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Organize the construction and functioning of transportation facilities and services",
            "b) Implementing strategies to manage the demand for transportation",
            "c) Establishing the linkage between land use strategies and transportation investments",
            "d) Review the management of various organizations responsible for road management in the country"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The function of Transportation organization is to organize the construction and functioning of transportation facilities and services. It also implements strategies to administer the growing demand for transportation.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 27,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an International Transport Organisations?",
        "Options": [
            "a) International Freight Forwarders Association",
            "b) International Air Transport Association",
            "c) International Maritime Health Association",
            "d) International Union of Railways"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: International Maritime Health Association is not an International Transport Organisations. It is an international organization that focuses on the quality of health of seafarers.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 28,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the best way to make public transportation efficient?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Separate bus lanes",
            "b) Carpooling",
            "c) Increasing tax",
            "d) Providing toll booths"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Separate bus lanes are the best way to make public transportation efficient. There should be a dedicated right of way for buses to warrant faster service.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 29,
        "Question": "Which administration represents the interests of truck, bus, coach and taxi operators for the transportation of people and commodities by roadway?",
        "Options": [
            "a) International Freight Forwarders Association",
            "b) National Highways Authority of India",
            "c) International Road Transport Union",
            "d) International Shipping Federation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: International Road Transport Union is the administration which represents the interests of truck, bus, coach and taxi operators for the transportation of people and commodities by roadway.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 30,
        "Question": "Which organization controls the State Road Transport Corporations?",
        "Options": [
            "a) International Road Transport Union",
            "b) National Highways Authority of India",
            "c) Association of State Road Transport Undertakings (ASTRU)",
            "d) Association of Management Development Institutions in South Asia"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Association of State Road Transport Undertakings (ASTRU) is the organization which controls the State Road Transport Corporations.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 31,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a category of Traffic Studies?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Inventories",
            "b) Administrative studies",
            "c) Dynamic studies",
            "d) Economic studies"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Traffic Studies is categorized into three main categories- Inventories, Administrative studies, and Dynamic studies.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 32,
        "Question": "Which of the following traffic study requires the collection of data under operational conditions?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dynamic studies",
            "b) Administrative studies",
            "c) Inventories",
            "d) Economic studies"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Dynamic studies requires the collection of data under operational conditions. It includes the study of speed, traffic volume, parking and travel and delay time.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 33,
        "Question": "Spot speed studies are conducted to ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) estimate distribution of speeds of vehicles in traffic at a particular location",
            "b) estimate distribution of traffic density at a particular location",
            "c) survey various locations based on speed",
            "d) survey various locations based on traffic density"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Spot speed studies are conducted to estimate the distribution of speeds of vehicles in traffic at a particular location. It is carried out by recording speeds of vehicles at a specified location.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 34,
        "Question": "Aerial photography and surveying are required in which type of traffic study?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Inventories",
            "b) Administrative studies",
            "c) Dynamic studies",
            "d) Detailed study"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Aerial photography and surveying is required in Administrative studies. This study uses existing records of the required location.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 35,
        "Question": "Pneumatic road tube device is a type of _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Manual data collection method",
            "b) Semi-automated data collection method",
            "c) Fully-automated data collection method",
            "d) None of the above"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It is true that goods movement and transit study is a type of traffic study. Records of existing truck loading facilities and transit system are made because these are important for proper planning and congestion.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 36,
        "Question": "Which of the following study is not conducted manually?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Traffic counts",
            "b) Intersection delay",
            "c) Operation of the traffic signal",
            "d) Travel time data"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Pneumatic road tube is a type of Semi-automated data collection method. Devices used in semi-automated data collection method are usually portable and so can be taken to various locations.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 37,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the prime disadvantage of fixed signal?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Data is available for a short period of time",
            "b) It is not portable",
            "c) Requires skills to use",
            "d) Costly"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Fully automated study makes use of permanently installed devices and sensors.  They are used to collect traffic data and to operate actuated or adaptive signals.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 38,
        "Question": "What is the error reported when using a stopwatch for manual study?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Time error",
            "b) Parallax",
            "c) Reading error",
            "d) Cumulative error"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Operation of the traffic signal is not conducted manually. It is nowadays done automatically.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 39,
        "Question": "What principle does radar meters use?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Doppler principle",
            "b) Van-Hoff principle",
            "c) Hooke’s law",
            "d) Tyndall effect"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The prime disadvantage of a fixed signal is that the data is not permanently stored in a retrievable form. It is only available in real time.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 40,
        "Question": "Radar meters must have a license from ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Indian Traffic Commission",
            "b) Federal Communication Commission",
            "c) Federal Traffic Commission",
            "d) Indian Communication Commission"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The error reported when using a stopwatch for the manual study is Parallax. It is a systematic error. Some minor adjustments can be done to remove it.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 41,
        "Question": "Pneumatic tubes are used for ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Traffic counting",
            "b) Surveying",
            "c) Parking counts",
            "d) Delay time"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Radar meter is based on the Doppler principle. The radar sends a wave that gets reflected from a moving vehicle. The difference between emitted and reflected frequency is proportional to speed.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 42,
        "Question": "What is the disadvantage of Pneumatic tubes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) They are costly",
            "b) They require skill",
            "c) They count the number of axles",
            "d) They are not portable"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Radar meters must have a license from the Federal Communication Commission (FCC). This license is made mandatory because radar meters emit within the federally regulated range of frequencies.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 43,
        "Question": "What was the first permanent detector used?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Inductive loop",
            "b) Pressure plate",
            "c) Magnetic detector",
            "d) Magnetometer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The first permanent detector used was Pressure plate. Two plates separated by rubber spring is connected to low voltage power source. When a vehicle moves over it, the two plates comes together completing the circuit and creating an electric pulse.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 44,
        "Question": "What is the principle used by the inductive loop?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Induction",
            "b) Electromagnetic field",
            "c) Doppler effect",
            "d) Scattering"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The principle used by the inductive loop is Electromagnetic field. When a vehicle enters the field of loop, inductance properties of loop decreases and the presence of a vehicle is recorded.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 45,
        "Question": "What is the standard loop detector size?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 12ft X 12ft",
            "b) 10ft X 10ft",
            "c) 6ft X 6ft",
            "d) 5ft X 5ft"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The standard loop detector size is 6ft X 6ft. And it covers only one lane. Longer loops are also available from size ranging from 6ft X 40ft to 6ft X 80ft.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 46,
        "Question": "Inductive loop directly measures ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Speed of vehicles",
            "b) Delay time",
            "c) Passage and presence of vehicles",
            "d) Travel time from one location to another"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Inductive loop measure’s passage and presence of vehicles. Speed and density of vehicles can be calibrated from algorithms.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 47,
        "Question": "What are the two types of magnetic detector?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Magnetometer and magnetic sensor",
            "b) Speed detector and magnetic sensor",
            "c) Magnetometer and speed detector",
            "d) Density detector and speed detector"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The two types of magnetic detector are magnetometer and a magnetic sensor. Magnetic detectors are a type of permanent detector.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 48,
        "Question": "Which magnetic detector can measure both passage and presence of vehicles?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Magnetometer",
            "b) Magnetic sensor",
            "c) Magnetometer and Magnetic sensor",
            "d) Speedometer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Magnetic detector which can measure both passage and presence of vehicles is Magnetometer. Magnetic sensor can detect only passage of vehicles.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 49,
        "Question": "What is the principle upon which the magnetic detector is based on?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Doppler effect",
            "b) Electromagnetic field",
            "c) Moving metal disturbs earth’s magnetic field",
            "d) Charles law"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The principle that magnetic detector is based on is that moving metal i.e. vehicles disturbs earth’s magnetic field. This disturbance is detected and counted.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 50,
        "Question": "What is the use of second wire loop on the Magnetometer?",
        "Options": [
            "a) To detect passage",
            "b) To detect presence",
            "c) To detect speed",
            "d) To detect density"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Magnetic detectors are placed under the roadway. They are also placed under the sub-base. They are used to estimate movement and presence of vehicles. Commonly used magnetic detectors are Magnetometer and Magnetic sensor.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 51,
        "Question": "Aerial photography uses which basic platform?",
        "Options": [
            "a) A stationary elevated vantage point",
            "b) Satellite",
            "c) Skydiving",
            "d) Hot air balloon"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The use of the second wire loop on the Magnetometer is to detect presence. Magnetic sensor has limited application since they are passage only magnetic detectors.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 52,
        "Question": "Which process captures individual vehicle traces through the photographed segment?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Aerial photography",
            "b) Digitizing",
            "c) Operating",
            "d) Tracing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Aerial photography uses three basic platforms. They are i) A stationary elevated vantage point, ii) fixed wing aircraft and iii) helicopters.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 53,
        "Question": "Which is the most desirable platform for aerial photography?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Elevated vantage point",
            "b) Fixed wing aircraft",
            "c) Helicopters",
            "d) Satellite"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The process which captures individual vehicle traces through the photographed segment is called digitizing. This process needs two or more fixed objects whose coordinates are known in every frame captured.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 54,
        "Question": "Which is the most suitable study for information on trip purpose?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Traffic counting",
            "b) Interview study",
            "c) Parking counts",
            "d) Tracking"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Elevated vantage point is the most desirable platform for aerial photography because throughout the study the camera is fixed. Aircraft and helicopters need to move and hover around which makes the camera non-stationary, which is not desirable for surveying.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 55,
        "Question": "In which of the following interview study traffic is disrupted?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Roadside interview",
            "b) Comprehensive home interview",
            "c) Destination-based interview",
            "d) Parking survey"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The most suitable study for information on trip purpose is Interview study. Some of the interview studies are Roadside interview, Comprehensive home interview, and destination based interview.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 56,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a factor that affects PRT?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Age",
            "b) Presence of alcohol in driver’s system",
            "c) Fatigue",
            "d) Vehicle accommodation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Age, presence of alcohol in driver’s system and fatigue are some of the factors that affect Perception Reaction Time (PRT) of a driver.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 57,
        "Question": "Within which field of vision should traffic signs be placed without the drivers having to change their line of sight?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Acute vision field",
            "b) Fairly clear vision field",
            "c) Peripheral vision field",
            "d) Obtuse vision field"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Traffic signs are to be placed in acute vision field so that the drivers can see them without changing their line of sight. As a result, they are set within a range of 3° – 10° around the line of sight.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 58,
        "Question": "What is the correct order of the four distinct processes a driver has to perform during perception and reaction time?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Detection, Identification, Decision, and Response",
            "b) Detection, Decision, Identification, and Response",
            "c) Identification, Detection, Decision, and Response",
            "d) Identification, Decision, Detection, and Response"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The correct order of the four distinct processes a driver has to perform during perception and reaction time is Detection, Identification, Decision, and Response. The driver first observes the object in front of the vehicle and then identifies it. Subsequently, the driver analyses the information and makes a decision and responses suitably.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 59,
        "Question": "What is the range of fairly clear vision cone?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10° – 15°",
            "b) 10° – 12°",
            "c) 3° – 10°",
            "d) 60° – 90°"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The peripheral vision field narrows as speed increases. The peripheral vision field ranges from 120° to 180°.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 60,
        "Question": "Some _______ pigment has been added to green lights and some ________ pigment has been added to red light to make it easier for the colourblind drivers to distinguish it.",
        "Options": [
            "a) blue, yellow",
            "b) red, green",
            "c) yellow, blue",
            "d) green, red"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: 10° – 12° is the range of fairly clear vision cone. Vision of the driver beyond this range is blurred.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 61,
        "Question": "What do Raised markers on a pavement indicate?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cycle trail",
            "b) Mandatory reduction in speed of the vehicle",
            "c) Railway track ahead",
            "d) Two-way lane demarcation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Some blue pigment has been added to green lights and some yellow pigment has been added to red light to make it easier for the colourblind drivers to distinguish it since colourblind people cannot distinguish between red and green.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 62,
        "Question": "Which visual reception affects the ability of a driver to estimate speed, distance, size, and acceleration?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hearing perception",
            "b) Depth perception",
            "c) Glare vision",
            "d) Visual acuity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Glare effects can be minimized by increasing the height of lights. It can also be decreased by reducing the brightness of light and positioning it farther from the roadway.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 63,
        "Question": "What is the recovery time when the driver moves from light to dark condition?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3 seconds",
            "b) 2 seconds",
            "c) 6 seconds",
            "d) 5 seconds"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Raised markers on a pavement indicate a mandatory reduction in speed of the vehicle on some highways.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 64,
        "Question": "What does the etching on the outside edge of the shoulder on a highway pavement indicate to a driver?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Vehicle leaving the pavement surface",
            "b) Vehicle entering a different lane",
            "c) Vehicle entering a construction site",
            "d) Vehicle entering the pedestrian lane"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The visual reception which affects the ability of a driver to estimate speed, distance, size, and acceleration is Depth perception. This is extremely important in two-way highways. Therefore traffic control devices are standard in size, shape, and colour to provide sufficient information to drivers to make important decisions.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 65,
        "Question": "The cone for peripheral vision is typically 160°. On what does this value depend on?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Speed of vehicle and hearing perception",
            "b) Speed of vehicle and age of driver",
            "c) Age of driver and depth perception",
            "d) Age of driver and glare recovery"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The recovery time when the driver moves from light to dark condition is 6 seconds. The recovery time when the driver moves from dark to light condition is 3 seconds. It is also termed as Glare recovery.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 66,
        "Question": "What is Gap Acceptance?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Minimum gap required to change the lane safely",
            "b) Maximum gap required to change the lane safely",
            "c) Minimum gap required in between parked cars",
            "d) Maximum gap required in between parked cars"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The etching on the outside edge of the shoulder on a highway pavement indicates to a driver that the vehicle is leaving the pavement surface.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 67,
        "Question": "The visibility difficulty that the driver faces at night is due to _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Depth perception",
            "b) Glare vision",
            "c) Visibility perception",
            "d) Colour blindness"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The cone for peripheral vision is typically about 160°. This value depends on the speed of vehicle and age of the driver. The range of peripheral vision is 120° to 180°.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 68,
        "Question": "What does PIEV mean?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Perception, Imitation, Environment, and Volition",
            "b) Perception, Identification, Environment, and Volition",
            "c) Perception, Identification, Emotion, and Volition",
            "d) Perception, Identification, Emotion, and Violation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: PIEV means Perception, Identification, Emotion, and Volition. This essentially means that a driver requires time to see and hear the action on the road and process it and act according to the circumstances on the road.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 69,
        "Question": "What are the factors that affect PRT?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Age, presence of alcohol and drugs, road rage, walking speed",
            "b) Age, presence of alcohol and drugs, fatigue, complexity of reactions",
            "c) Age, presence of alcohol and drugs, fatigue, size of obstruction",
            "d) Age, presence of alcohol and drugs, fatigue, type of pavement"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The factors that affect PRT are age, presence of alcohol and drugs, fatigue and complexity of reactions. Expectancy is also a significant factor affecting PRT i.e. drivers will react more quickly to circumstances they expect to stumble upon.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 70,
        "Question": "What is the Perception Reaction Time for braking on highways?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 second",
            "b) 2.5 seconds",
            "c) 3.5 seconds",
            "d) 3 seconds"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The Perception Reaction Time (PRT) for braking on highways is 2.5 seconds. The Perception Reaction Time (PRT) for reaction time to traffic signals is 1 second. These recommendations are specified by AASHTO.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 71,
        "Question": "The initial speed of the vehicle is 80 kmph. What is the reaction distance?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 45.5 m",
            "b) 55.2 m",
            "c) 55.6 m",
            "d) 22.24 m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: d = 0.278 S.t\n \t         here,\n\t\t       d = reaction distance\n\t\t       S = initial speed of vehicle, kmph\n\t\t       t = reaction time, s = 2.5 seconds\n\t        d = 0.278 X 80 X 2.5 = 55.6 kmph\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 72,
        "Question": "A vehicle travels at a speed of 60 kmph. The driver then sees a stopped car on the road ahead. How far will the driver’s vehicle travel before the driver’s foot reach the brake?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 41.7 m",
            "b) 40 m",
            "c) 31.2 m",
            "d) 45 m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: d = 0.278 S.t\n\t         here,\n\t\t       d = reaction distance\n\t\t       S = initial speed of vehicle, kmph\n\t\t       t = reaction time, s = 2.5 seconds\n\t         d = 0.278 X 60 X 2.5 = 41.7 kmph\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 73,
        "Question": "The driver notices a red traffic signal towards the front. The vehicle moves 11m before he can observe and apply brakes on the vehicle. At what speed the vehicle was moving?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 30 kmph",
            "b) 40 kmph",
            "c) 50 kmph",
            "d) 60 kmph"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: d = 0.278 S.t\n\t         here,\n\t\t       d = reaction distance\n\t\t       S = initial speed of vehicle, kmph\n\t\t       t = reaction time, s = 1 seconds for reaction on a traffic signal\n\t\t       d = 0.278 X S X 1\n\t\t     11 = 0.278 X S X 1\n\t\t      S  = 11/0.278 = 39.5 kmph = 40 kmph (approx.)\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 74,
        "Question": "What is the AASHTO recommendation for a PRT for stops on rural roads where collision avoidance maneuver is required?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 9.1 seconds",
            "b) 10 seconds",
            "c) 8 seconds",
            "d) 3 seconds"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The AASHTO recommendation for a PRT for stops on rural roads where collision avoidance maneuver is required is 3 seconds. It is 9.1 seconds for urban roads.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 75,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a category of expectancy?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Continuity",
            "b) Event",
            "c) Temporal",
            "d) Complexity of reaction"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Complexity of reaction is not a category of expectancy but it is one of the factors affecting PRT. Continuity, Event, and Temporal are the types of expectancy.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 76,
        "Question": "A driver with a perception-reaction time of 2.5s is driving with a speed of 75 kmph. He observes an accident on the road ahead. Workout the distance the vehicle will travel before the driver applies brakes.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 49 m",
            "b) 52 m",
            "c) 50 m",
            "d) 53 m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: d = 0.278 S.t\n\t         here,\n\t\t       d = reaction distance\n\t\t       S = initial speed of vehicle, kmph\n\t\t       t = reaction time, s = 2.5 seconds\n\t\t       d = 0.278 X S X 2.5\n\t\t       d = 0.278 X S X 2.5\n\t\t       d = 52.125 m = 52 m (approx.)\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 77,
        "Question": "What is the AASHTO recommendation for a PRT on urban roads where collision avoidance requires speed, path and direction changes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 14 to 14.5 seconds",
            "b) 10.2 to 11.2 seconds",
            "c) 12.1 to 12.9 seconds",
            "d) 9.1 to 9.9 seconds"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The AASHTO recommendation for a PRT on urban roads where collision avoidance requires speed, path, and direction changes is 14 to 14.5 seconds. It is 10.2 to 11.2 seconds for rural roads and 12.1 to 12.9 seconds for suburban roads.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 78,
        "Question": "What can be done to avoid Expectant accidents on the road?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Set up Speed limits",
            "b) Two lane roads",
            "c) Guide signs",
            "d) Speed breakers"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Guide signs are to be carefully designed and erected on the left-hand ramp to alert the drivers and make it “unexpected”. If there are all right-hand ramps then avoid left-hand ramps.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 79,
        "Question": "In how many categories are motor vehicles classified by AASHTO?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4",
            "b) 5",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Motor vehicles are classified by AASHTO into four main categories and they are Passenger cars (SUVs, minivans, pickup trucks), Buses (transit buses, school buses), Trucks (single unit trucks, tractor-trailer, tractor semi-trailer combination vehicles) and Recreational vehicles (cars with various types of trailers).\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 80,
        "Question": "Which of the following is critical vehicle property for the design of roadways and traffic control?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Type of engine",
            "b) Type of fuel the vehicle runs on",
            "c) Acceleration",
            "d) Age of vehicle"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Acceleration is one of the critical vehicle property for the design of roadways and traffic con-trol. Braking and deceleration, low speed and high speed turning characteristics are also some of the criti-cal vehicle property required for the design of roadways and traffic control.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 81,
        "Question": "How many design vehicles has AASHTO specified for geometric design of road?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10",
            "b) 11",
            "c) 13",
            "d) 20"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: AASHTO has specified 20 design vehicles, each with specified characteristics for geometric design of the road. Some of the design vehicles as specified by AASHTO are P for passenger cars, SU for single truck unit, BUS-40 for intercity bus with 40ft wheelbase.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 82,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the incorrect use of Design vehicles?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Design of turning roadways",
            "b) Design of intersection curbs",
            "c) Determination of lane widths",
            "d) Design of different types of vehicles"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Design vehicles are used for the design of turning roadways and intersection curbs primarily. It is also used to determine lane widths such as lane widening on curves.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 83,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the minimum design vehicle for local street applications?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Passenger car",
            "b) Single-unit truck",
            "c) Intercity bus",
            "d) Triple semi-trailer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The minimum design vehicle for local street applications is Single-unit truck because hook and ladder fire vehicles have rear axle steering that allows the vehicle to negotiate sharp turns, so the use of the single unit truck is not considered to hinder emergency vehicle.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 84,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the design vehicle for parking lots?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Passenger car",
            "b) Single-unit truck",
            "c) Intercity bus",
            "d) Triple semi-trailer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The design vehicle generally used for parking lots is Passenger car (P). Access to emergency vehicles is also considered in the design of parking lots in all the buildings and public places.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 85,
        "Question": "For the design of highways and intersections, the selection of design vehicle must consider __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Vehicle length",
            "b) Vehicle mix",
            "c) Emergency vehicles",
            "d) Topography"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: For the design of highways and intersections, the selection of design vehicle must consider the expected vehicle mix. The design vehicle should accommodate 95% or more of the expected vehicle mix.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 86,
        "Question": "What is the height range of design vehicles?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4.25 ft—13.5 ft",
            "b) 4.5 ft—13.5 ft",
            "c) 4.25 ft—14 ft",
            "d) 4.25 ft—15 ft"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The height range of design vehicles is 4.25 ft for passenger vehicles and 13.5 ft for large trucks. According to this range, design of roadways is accomplished.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 87,
        "Question": "What is the minimum clearance for most facilities?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 15 ft",
            "b) 15 ft",
            "c) 10 ft",
            "d) 14 ft"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The minimum clearance for most facilities is 14 ft. This is so because all facilities must ac-commodate emergency vehicles.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 88,
        "Question": "What is the width range of design vehicles?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 7 ft — 8.5 ft",
            "b) 5 ft — 10 ft",
            "c) 2 ft — 8 ft",
            "d) 4 ft — 10 ft"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The width range of design vehicles is 7 ft for passenger vehicles and 8.5 ft for large trucks. This data influences the design of lane width and shoulders.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 89,
        "Question": "What is the desirable lane width for facilities?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 12 ft",
            "b) 13 ft",
            "c) 10 ft",
            "d) 5 ft"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The desirable lane width for facilities is 12 ft. 10 ft is the minimum lane width for all applica-tions where area is restricted. This is mandatory for easy flow of vehicles moving in and out of the facility.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 90,
        "Question": "What are the conditions under which vehicles must take turns?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Low speed turns and high speed turns",
            "b) Superelevation",
            "c) Wheel load",
            "d) Centrifugal force"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The conditions under which vehicles must take turns are low speed turns (less than or equal to 16 kmph) and high speed turns (more than or equal to 16kmph).\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 91,
        "Question": "Low speed turns are limited by _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Characteristics of vehicle",
            "b) Dynamics of side friction",
            "c) Wheel load",
            "d) Type of road"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Low-speed turns are limited by characteristics of the vehicle because the minimum radius al-lowed by the vehicle’s steering mechanism can be supported at such speeds.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 92,
        "Question": "High speed turns are limited by ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Characteristics of vehicle",
            "b) Dynamics of side friction",
            "c) Wheel load",
            "d) Type of road"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: High speed turns are limited by dynamics of side friction between road and tires. They are also limited by the superelevation of road.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 93,
        "Question": "The characteristic WB-40 indicates which design vehicle?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Intermediate semi-trailer ( wheelbase = 40 ft)",
            "b) Intermediate semi-trailer ( wheelbase = 50 ft)",
            "c) Intermediate semi-trailer ( wheelbase = 62 ft)",
            "d) Inter bus city (wheelbase = 40 ft)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The characteristic WB-40 indicates Intermediate semi-trailer ( wheelbase = 40 ft) design vehi-cle. This characteristic is recommended by AASHTO. It has 20 such design vehicles which are useful for de-sign of roadways.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 94,
        "Question": "Which technique can be used to judge pedestrian behaviour?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Traffic survey",
            "b) Interview study",
            "c) Calibration study",
            "d) Observation study"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The technique that can be used to judge pedestrian behaviour is Interview study. Interview studies can be done to judge walking pattern of the pedestrian on the street. Questionnaire is done in this study.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 95,
        "Question": "Which main trait is obtained from Pedestrian study?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Crosswalks at signalized and un-signalized intersection",
            "b) Crosswalks at flyovers",
            "c) Pedestrian’s origin and destination",
            "d) Pedestrian’s traffic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The main trait that is obtained from Pedestrian study is their mode in using crosswalks at sig-nalized and un-signalized intersection. Pedestrian study helps understand the pattern of the pedestrian and determines whether retiming is required or not in a signalised intersection.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 96,
        "Question": "What is the standard speed at which pedestrians cross the crosswalks?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3-5ft/s",
            "b) 2-3ft/s",
            "c) 5-7ft/s",
            "d) 1-3ft/s"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The standard speed at which pedestrians cross the crosswalks is 3-5ft/s. A survey among both men and women were conducted to get this result.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 97,
        "Question": "Bicycle LOS is based on __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Quality of service linked to the comfort of car drivers",
            "b) Quality of service linked to the comfort of cyclists",
            "c) Speed of cycles",
            "d) Density of cycles"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Bicycle LOS is based on the quality of service linked to comfort of the cyclists. It does not rely on the speed of cycles or density of cycles on the roadway.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 98,
        "Question": "Warning signs dealing with pedestrians and cyclists have which colour background?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Red",
            "b) Lime Green",
            "c) Yellow",
            "d) Black"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Warning signs dealing with pedestrians and cyclists have lime green colour background. Most warning signs have yellow background, black letters or symbols and are diamond shaped.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 99,
        "Question": "What are the two approaches considered when minimum pedestrian condition is not met?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pedestrian actuator and retiming of signal",
            "b) Pedestrian actuator and redesigning",
            "c) Retiming of signal and traffic controller",
            "d) Traffic controller and crossway broadened"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Two approaches considered when minimum pedestrian condition is not met are Pedestrian actuator and retiming of signal. But when a pedestrian actuator is provided, a pedestrian signal must be used.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 100,
        "Question": "What is the standard walking speed used in timing signals where older pedestrians are dominant?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4ft/s",
            "b) 5ft/s",
            "c) 2ft/s",
            "d) 3.5ft/s"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The standard walking speed used in timing signals where older pedestrians are dominant is 3.5ft/s. Usually when this is not the case the timing used is 4ft/s.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 101,
        "Question": "What is the main demerit of retiming the traffic signal for pedestrians and cyclists?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Delay of vehicles",
            "b) Delay of pedestrians and cyclist",
            "c) Accidents",
            "d) Disruption of traffic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Pedestrian actuators are useful when pedestrians are scarce is a true statement. Pedestrian actuators are also used where actuated signal controllers are used.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 102,
        "Question": "Which of the following formula gives the amount of time needed for pedestrians to safely cross the crosswalk in a pre-timed traffic signal?",
        "Options": [
            "a) G = 3.2 – 0.27 Npeds + L/S",
            "b) G = 3.2 + 0.27 Npeds + L/S",
            "c) G = 0.27 Npeds + L/S",
            "d) G = 3.2 + 0.27 Npeds"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The main demerit of retiming the traffic signal for pedestrians and cyclists is the delay of vehi-cles. Retiming generally increases the red light time for the vehicles and this causes increase in time to get to their destination.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 103,
        "Question": "What should be done when minimum green does not provide safe crossing for pedestrians?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Crosswalk removed",
            "b) Retiming of signal",
            "c) Traffic controller",
            "d) Pedestrian push button"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The formula which gives the amount of time needed for pedestrians to safely cross the crosswalk in a pre—timed traffic signal is,\n  \t\t\tG = 3.2 – 0.27 Npeds + L/S\n\t\t\there,\n\t\t\t        G = Amount of time needed for pedestrians to safely cross the          \t\t\t              crosswalk or Pedestrian green time\n\t\t\t        C = Amount of time for safe crossing of pedestrians\n\t\t\t        Npeds = Number of pedestrians\n\t\t\t        L = Length of crosswalk\n\t\t\t        S = Walking speed of pedestrians.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 104,
        "Question": "What is the minimum width of footpath in India for commercial areas?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2m",
            "b) 3m",
            "c) 1.8m",
            "d) 2.5m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The minimum width of footpath in India for commercial areas is 2.5m. It is 1.8m for residential areas. The width should be adequate for two wheelchairs to cross each other.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 105,
        "Question": "What is the minimum width of cycling path?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.5m",
            "b) 2m",
            "c) 4m",
            "d) 5m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The minimum width of cycling path is 2m. This width is considered when right of way widths do not consider separate cycling path. Usually a cycling path has a clear width of 2.5m.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 106,
        "Question": "Which of the following is one of the 8 climate mission of the Government of India?",
        "Options": [
            "a) National Mission on Sustainable Habitat",
            "b) Nehemiah Sustainable Vision Engagement",
            "c) National Mission on Climate Change",
            "d) National Mission on Transportation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: One of the 8 climate mission of the Government of India is National Mission on Sustainable Habitat. It was introduced to form sustainable cities that prioritize energy efficiency and public transport especially pedestrians, cyclist, etc.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 107,
        "Question": "What is the act which refers to the ease of access to offices, public buildings, and transport infrastructure?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rights of Person with Disability Act, 2016",
            "b) Rights of Specially Abled Act, 2016",
            "c) Disabled People Right, 2016",
            "d) Rights of Person with Disability Act, 2015"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The act which refers to the ease of access to offices, public buildings, and transport infrastructure is Rights of Person with Disability Act, 2016. This act bargains with the issues faced by differently abled people.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 108,
        "Question": "What was the issue identified in IRC:106, 1990 (Guidelines for Capacity if Urban Roads in Plain Areas)?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Doesn’t address cycle infrastructure",
            "b) Cycle as a mode was not considered",
            "c) Parking space for NMT is absent",
            "d) Identifies cycle as a threat"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The issue identified in IRC:106, 1990 (Guidelines for Capacity if Urban Roads in Plain Areas) is that cycle as a mode was not considered. Another issue was to improve the capacity of roadway, and suggestion was made to impose constrain on slow-moving vehicle.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 109,
        "Question": "Which of the following factors does not affect the NMT network?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Reduction of speed of motorized vehicles",
            "b) Merging safest and fastest route",
            "c) Signalized paths",
            "d) Improving visibility at intersections"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The factor which does not affect the NMT network is signalized paths for Non-Motorised Transport network. Signals are not required in a Non-Motorised Transport path.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 110,
        "Question": "What is the data source for Trip Production Pattern in an NMT plan?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Household Interview Data",
            "b) Ward Map",
            "c) Property Tax Data",
            "d) Traffic Volume Counts"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The data source for Trip Production Pattern in an NMT plan is Household Interview Data. Comprehensive Mobility Plan of the city is also a data source for Trip Production Pattern in an NMT plan. Traffic Volume Counts are for Traffic Assignment.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 111,
        "Question": "Why is Travel Demand Model required?",
        "Options": [
            "a) To recreate the road network and travel pattern",
            "b) To recreate the road network only",
            "c) To recreate the travel pattern only",
            "d) To recreate the travel pattern and footpaths"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Travel Demand Model is required to recreate the road network and travel pattern. This model is used in modelling software to test various measures to refine the existing NMT network.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 112,
        "Question": "Trip distribution in NMT is carried out based on _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pedestrian Compatibility Index",
            "b) Cycle Compatibility Index",
            "c) Vehicle Compatibility Index",
            "d) Trip Compatibility Index"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Trip distribution in NMT (Non-Motorised Transport) is carried out based on the Cycle Compatibility Index (BCI). This index was introduced by University of North Carolina Highway Safety Research Centre.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 113,
        "Question": "What is the data source for Road Network in an NMT plan?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Household Interview Data",
            "b) Ward Map",
            "c) Property Tax Data",
            "d) Land Use Data"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Property Tax Data is the data source which provides information for Road Network in an NMT plan. Other data sources are primary data for road inventory and link speeds and secondary data on road widths.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 114,
        "Question": "What is the WALK interval when the number of pedestrians is 10?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4 s",
            "b) 5.9 s",
            "c) 6.2 s",
            "d) 10 s"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: WALK = 3.2 + 0.27 Npeds\n\t                           = 3.2 + 0.27 X 10 = 5.9 s.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 115,
        "Question": "How many travel movements are present on a typical trip?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5",
            "b) 6",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: There are 6 types of travel movements on a typical trip as per AASHTO. Main Movement, Transition, Distribution, Collection, Access, and Termination are the 6 types of travel movements in a typical trip as per AASHTO.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 116,
        "Question": "Which travel movement occurs when vehicle transfers from the through portion of trip to the remaining travel movement functions?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Main Movement",
            "b) Access",
            "c) Transition",
            "d) Distribution"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The travel movement which occurs when vehicle transfers from the through portion of the trip to the remaining travel movement function is Transition. For example, a vehicle uses ramp transition from a freeway to a surface arterial.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 117,
        "Question": "In how many groups are highways classified based on access and mobility?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3",
            "b) 4",
            "c) 6",
            "d) 2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Highways are classified into 4 groups based on access and mobility. The four major classes of highways are Limited-access facilities, Arterials, Collectors and Local street.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 118,
        "Question": "Which class of highway classification provides 100% mobility?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Arterials",
            "b) Collectors",
            "c) Limited-access facilities",
            "d) Local street"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Limited-access facilities is the class of highway classification that provides 100% mobility. But access to bordering land is prohibited.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 119,
        "Question": "The function of arterial can be strengthened by which of the following options?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Incorporating sharp curvature",
            "b) Use of cul-de-sacs",
            "c) Not having any residence in front of collector",
            "d) Limiting the number of locations of entry and exit on the arterial"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The given statement is false. Arterials are surface facilities designed essentially for through movement of vehicles. They permit some access to abutting land.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 120,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a primary element of the geometry of a highway section?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Horizontal alignment",
            "b) Vertical alignment",
            "c) Cross-sectional element",
            "d) Traffic Signals"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: By limiting the number of locations of entry and exit on the arterial, the function of arterial can be strengthened. Incorporating sharp curvature and use of cul-de-sacs strengthens the function of local street. Not having any residence in front of collector strengthens the function of collector.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 121,
        "Question": "Which of the following is an important consideration for designing Horizontal alignment?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Social consideration",
            "b) Aesthetics",
            "c) Maintenance of comfortable operations",
            "d) Superelevation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The given statement is true. Coordinated signals provided for continuous progressive movement at appropriate speed to strengthen the function of arterial. Parking prohibition also strengthens the function of arterial.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 122,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an Engineering factor?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Topography",
            "b) Natural barriers",
            "c) Forecast demand volumes",
            "d) Drainage patterns"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Traffic Signals is not a primary element of the geometry of a highway section. Horizontal alignment, vertical alignment, and cross-sectional element are the primary elements that govern the geometry of a highway.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 123,
        "Question": "What is the unit of Grade in a vertical alignment?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Meter",
            "b) Hectare",
            "c) Dimensionless",
            "d) Kilograms"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Social consideration is is an important factor when designing a Horizontal alignment. Forecast demand volumes, patterns of development and natural barriers are some of the factors that are considered when designing a Horizontal alignment.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 124,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a primary design criterion for vertical curves?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Drainage",
            "b) Forecast demand volumes",
            "c) Sub-surface conditions",
            "d) Natural barriers"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Forecast demand volumes is not an Engineering factor. It deals with demand prediction and specific origin and destination of vehicles.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 125,
        "Question": "Which of the following is an important consideration for designing cross-sections of a highway?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Superelevation",
            "b) Topography",
            "c) Forecast demand volumes",
            "d) Sub-surface conditions"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Grade in a vertical alignment is a dimensionless quantity. Grade is the longitudinal slope of a roadway. It is represented with a decimal or percentage.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 126,
        "Question": "If the degree of curvature is higher then the curve is ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) sharper",
            "b) flatter",
            "c) vertical",
            "d) elliptical"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The above statement, “A Spiral transition curve has a varying radius” is true. It starts with its radius at infinity and then ends at the radius of the circular curve.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 127,
        "Question": "What is the maximum side slope of cut and fill section where sandy soil is predominant?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1:2",
            "b) 3:1",
            "c) 6:1",
            "d) 10:1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: If the degree of curvature is higher then the curve is sharper. The severity of the circular horizontal curve is Degree of curvature.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 128,
        "Question": "What is the maximum superelevation in snowy areas?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5%",
            "b) 6%",
            "c) 3%",
            "d) 8%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The maximum side slope of cut and fill section where sandy soil is predominant is 6:1. 3:1 is the maximum side slope of cut and fill section for the safe functioning of maintenance and mowing actions.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 129,
        "Question": "The value of side-friction factor varies with ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) design speed",
            "b) superelevation",
            "c) skidding",
            "d) overturning"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The maximum superelevation in snowy areas is 8%. Superelevation is the total rise of roadway from edge to edge span of the roadway.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 130,
        "Question": "In how many stages does the transition from a tangent section to super-elevated horizontal curve takes place?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 4",
            "d) 5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The value of side friction varies with design speed. Side-friction factor also represents frictional forces that can be easily accomplished.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 131,
        "Question": "Length of the transition curve is the maximum of length due to _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) centrifugal force, superelevation, and empirical",
            "b) centrifugal force, superelevation, and tangent",
            "c) superelevation, centripetal, and empirical",
            "d) superelevation, centripetal, and design speed"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In 2 stages, the transition from a tangent section to super-elevated horizontal curve takes place. Tangent runoff and superelevation runoff are the two stages of transition.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 132,
        "Question": "Which one of the following is not an advantage of spiral transition?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Easy path for drivers to follow",
            "b) Aesthetics",
            "c) Agreeable arrangement of superelevation runoff",
            "d) Less delay"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Length of transition curve is the maximum of length due to centrifugal force, superelevation, and empirical. Transition curve is the horizontal curve provided between straight alignment to a circular curve for a smooth transition.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 133,
        "Question": "The distance from the centreline of the inside lane to the nearest roadside sight blockage is called.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Length of curve",
            "b) Apex",
            "c) Mid-ordinate",
            "d) Tangent"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Less delay is not an advantage of spiral transition. Easy path for drivers to follow, aesthetics, and agreeable arrangement of superelevation runoff are the advantages of spiral transition.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 134,
        "Question": "What are the two types of vertical curves?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Crest and sag",
            "b) Crest and plume",
            "c) Sag and sink",
            "d) Sink and fall"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation:  The distance from the centreline of the inside lane to the nearest roadside sight blockage is called Mid-ordinate. The formula for mid-ordinate is,\n  \t\t    M = R(1-cos θ/2)\n              where, M = mid-ordinate\n                         R = radius of curvature\n                         θ = angle of deflection.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 135,
        "Question": "What is the mid-ordinate of a curve with a radius of curvature 2m and angle of deflection = 60°?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.342",
            "b) 0.268",
            "c) 0.112",
            "d) 0.245"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The two types of vertical curves are crest and sag. Crest, as the name suggests, is a vertical curve having its entry tangent grade greater than the exit tangent grade. While sag has its entry tangent grade smaller than its exit tangent grade.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 136,
        "Question": "The sight distance in a sag vertical curve is limited by which factor given below during night time driving condition?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Design speed",
            "b) Driver’s height",
            "c) Headlamp range",
            "d) Ruling speed"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: M = R(1-cos θ/2)\nwhere, M = mid-ordinate\n           R = radius of curvature\n           θ = angle of deflection\nM = R(1-cos θ/2) = 2(1-cos60/2) = 0.268 m.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 137,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a feature of cross-section elements of a highway?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Shoulders",
            "b) Side slopes",
            "c) Curbs",
            "d) Signal"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The sight distance in a sag vertical curve is limited by Headlamp range during night time driving condition. Sight distance is the length visible to the driver while travelling on the road.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 138,
        "Question": "The number of vehicles crossing a section of road in a unit time at any selected period is called ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Traffic volume study",
            "b) Traffic density study",
            "c) Traffic mass study",
            "d) Traffic characteristic study"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The number of vehicles crossing a section of road in a unit time at any selected period is called Traffic volume study. Its unit is vehicles/hr or vehicles/day.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 139,
        "Question": "Speed studies are conducted for what primary purpose?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Traffic census",
            "b) Safety",
            "c) Quality of service",
            "d) Planning"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Speed studies are conducted primarily for safety purpose. Speed characteristics are needed to be assessed from time to time for safety concerns. New speed limits are set if the current one is not viable.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 140,
        "Question": "Demand-forecasting model is based on which traffic studies?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Speed studies",
            "b) Traffic volume study",
            "c) Travel time studies",
            "d) Accident studies"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Demand-forecasting model is based on Travel time studies. Travel time along sections of highways comprises of a major measure of the quality of service to users.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 141,
        "Question": "Total parking demand is determined by which traffic study?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Accident studies",
            "b) Traffic volume study",
            "c) Travel time studies",
            "d) Parking studies"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Total parking demand is determined by Parking studies type of traffic study. Several counting methodologies are used to determine the parking need of people. Interview studies are done to see how parking facilities are used.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 142,
        "Question": "Which traffic study records the existing truck loading facilities and transit system?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Goods movement and Transit studies",
            "b) Parking studies",
            "c) Traffic volume studies",
            "d) Travel time studies"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Goods movement and Transit studies record the existing truck loading facilities and transit system. It is a significant factor of congestion, proper planning, and operation policies.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 143,
        "Question": "Which traffic study uses traffic models to analyze traffic?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Traffic volume studies",
            "b) Calibration studies",
            "c) Parking studies",
            "d) Accident studies"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Calibration studies use traffic models to analyze traffic. Studies are done to calibrate key values in models to guarantee that they depict the conditions in real-life traffic.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 144,
        "Question": "Which traffic study studies the effectiveness of various traffic control devices?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Calibration studies",
            "b) Observation studies",
            "c) Parking studies",
            "d) Traffic volume studies"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Observation studies the effectiveness of various traffic control devices. It assesses the design of the control devices and studies how it is implemented. It helps evaluate control measures.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 145,
        "Question": "The time lost by traffic due to traffic friction and traffic control devices is called _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) Delay",
            "b) Green time",
            "c) Red time",
            "d) Setback time"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The time lost by traffic due to traffic friction and traffic control devices is called delay. Delay is the added time spent by the drivers against their presumption.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 146,
        "Question": "The delay caused by the intervention by other components of traffic is called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Operational delay",
            "b) Fixed delay",
            "c) Stopped delay",
            "d) Approach delay"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The delay caused by the intervention by other components of traffic is called Operational delay. Some examples of this delay are, time lost due to parking manoeuvres, pedestrians, and turning movement.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 147,
        "Question": "What is the difference between the actual time required to cross a section of a road and the time taken corresponding to the average speed of traffic under free-flow condition called?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Travel time delay",
            "b) Congestion delay",
            "c) Stopped Delay",
            "d) Approach Delay"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Traffic islands are used to decrease the length of the crossing. This is done so for the safe crossing of pedestrians and easy flow of traffic.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 148,
        "Question": "The total time of travel, including stop and delay, to travel from one point of a section to another under existing traffic condition is called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Operational delay",
            "b) Travel time",
            "c) Fixed delay",
            "d) Approach delay"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The total time of travel, including stop and delay, to travel from one point of a section to another under existing traffic condition is called Travel time. There are various techniques to determine travel time. Some of them are floating car method, average speed method, and elevated observation method.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 149,
        "Question": "What is the purpose of a Travel Time and Delay Study?",
        "Options": [
            "a) To assess the quality of traffic movement",
            "b) To assess the time taken to travel by various vehicles",
            "c) To evaluate the traffic stream",
            "d) For survey data"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: To assess the quality of traffic movement along a roadway and to determine the traffic delays, using a test vehicle, is the purpose of a Travel Time and Delay Study.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 150,
        "Question": "In which of the following cases Travel Time and Delay Study is not used?",
        "Options": [
            "a) To compare operational conditions before and after enhancements have been made",
            "b) To compare operational inadequacies in each project",
            "c) To monitor LOS of road",
            "d) To compare the design width of the road in each condition"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Travel Time and Delay Study is used to compare operational conditions before and after enhancements have been made, to compare operational inadequacies in each project, and to monitor LOS of road.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 151,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a method for obtaining travel time and delay studies?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Floating car method",
            "b) Average speed method",
            "c) Interview method",
            "d) Spot speed method"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Spot speed method is not a method for obtaining travel time and delay studies. It is a method which helps us to determine the geometry of superelevation and horizontal and vertical curves.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 152,
        "Question": "In which of the following methods given below does the observer travels and makes a round trip along a test section in a traffic stream?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Floating car method",
            "b) Average speed method",
            "c) Spot speed method",
            "d) License plate method"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In Average speed method the observer travels and makes a round trip along a test section in a traffic stream. In this method, the driver drives the test car at an average speed of the test route and the time taken to complete that distance is noted.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 153,
        "Question": "Which given formula gives the volume of traffic in westbound direction?",
        "Options": [
            "a) qw = (ma+mo-mp)/(ta+tw)",
            "b) qw = (ma+mo-mp)/(ta-tw)",
            "c) qw = (ma-mo-mp)/(ta+tw)",
            "d) qw = (ma+mo+mp)/(ta+tw)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: qw = (ma+mo-mp)/(ta+tw), is the formula that gives the volume of traffic in westbound direction. Here, qw = volume of traffic in westbound direction, ma = number of vehicle travelling east in opposite lane, mo = number of vehicles that overtake the test car, mp = number of vehicles that the test car passes when it is travelling westwards, ta = time taken to travel to east and tw = time taken to travel to west.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 154,
        "Question": "In which method a test vehicle is selected at random?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Elevated observation method",
            "b) Average speed method",
            "c) License plate method",
            "d) Floating car method"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Elevated observation method is a Travel Time and Delay Study method which selects a test vehicle at random. Here observation is done from a high building or an elevated point from where the whole test route is clearly visible.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 155,
        "Question": "Which travel time and delay study method is usually adopted in a farm or an establishment?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Photographic method",
            "b) Elevated observation method",
            "c) License plate method",
            "d) Interview method"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The statement, “Photographic method is suitable only for long test sections” is false. “Photographic method is suitable only for short test sections’’ is the true statement. It is useful for the study of the interrelationship between speeds, spacing, acceleration rates, merging and crossing manoeuvres, etc.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 156,
        "Question": "Average travel time in westbound direction is obtained from which of the given formula?",
        "Options": [
            "a) tw(avg) = tw-((mo-mp)/qw)",
            "b) tw(avg) = tw+((mo-mp)/qw)",
            "c) tw(avg) = tw-((mo-mp)+qw)",
            "d) tw(avg) = tw-((mo+mp)/qw)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Interview method is usually adopted large quantity of material is required in limited time and at little cost for field observation. These are preferably conducted where there is a farm or an establishment. Employees are asked to document their travel time to and from work.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 157,
        "Question": "Which method is applicable for under saturated signalized intersection?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Highway Capacity Manual 2000",
            "b) Photographic method",
            "c) License plate method",
            "d) Elevated observation method"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Average travel time in westbound direction is obtained from,\ntw(avg) = tw-((mo-mp)/qw)\nwhere, tw(avg) = Average travel time in westbound direction\n\tmo = number of vehicles that overtake the test car\n           mp = number of vehicles that the test car passes when it is travelling westwards\n           tw = time taken to travel to the west.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 158,
        "Question": "What is the correct order of procedure in a License plate method?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Portable computer, Manual, Video with manual transcription, Video with character recognition",
            "b) Manual, Portable computer, Video with manual transcription, Video with character recognition",
            "c) Video with manual transcription, Video with character recognition, Portable computer, Manual",
            "d) Video with manual transcription, Video with character recognition, Manual, Portable computer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Highway Capacity Manual 2000 is travel time and delay study method which is applicable for under saturated signalized intersection. Queue buildup in over-saturated conditions makes the method unfeasible.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 159,
        "Question": "What is Passenger Car Unit used for?",
        "Options": [
            "a) to evaluate the traffic-flow rate on a highway",
            "b) to record the number of passengers in each car",
            "c) to record the number of passengers in each section of road",
            "d) to evaluate the density of passengers"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Passenger Car Unit used to evaluate the traffic-flow rate on a highway. Passenger Car Unit is also generally known as passenger car equivalent. PCU is a metric used in transportation engineering.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 160,
        "Question": "What is the Passenger Car Unit (PCU) value of a motorcycle?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 0.5",
            "c) 0.2",
            "d) 0.3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The Passenger Car Unit (PCU) value of a motorcycle is 0.5. 1 and 0.2 are the Passenger Car Unit values of car and bicycle respectively.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 161,
        "Question": "What is the unit of highway capacity?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Veh/hr",
            "b) PCU/hr",
            "c) Veh/hr/section of road",
            "d) PCU/section of road"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: PCU/hr is the unit of highway capacity. Highway Capacity is the maximum traffic flow that can be accommodated in a highway during a given time period under existing roadway, traffic and control conditions.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 162,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a factor affecting PCU?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Vehicles characteristic",
            "b) Traffic stream characteristic",
            "c) Roadway characteristic",
            "d) Design characteristic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Design characteristic is not a factor affecting PCU. Vehicles characteristic, traffic stream characteristic, roadway characteristic, and regulation and control of traffic are some the factors affecting PCU.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 163,
        "Question": "PCU value is the fraction of capacity of a road where there are passenger cars only to the ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) capacity of the same road when there are vehicles of that class",
            "b) capacity of a different road when there are vehicles of that class",
            "c) capacity of the same road when there are vehicles of a different class",
            "d) capacity of the different road when there are vehicles of a different class"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: PCU value is the fraction of capacity of a road where there are passenger cars only to the capacity of the same road when there are vehicles of that class. PCU is the measure of space required by the vehicle class compared to passenger cars.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 164,
        "Question": "Passenger Car Unit is an estimate of the impact that a mode of transport has on ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) traffic system",
            "b) traffic variables",
            "c) traffic signals",
            "d) design"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Passenger Car Unit (PCU) is an estimate of the impact that a mode of transport has on traffic variables. Traffic variables are speed, density, headway, etc.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 165,
        "Question": "Which of the following method is used to determine PCU?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Multiple linear regression method",
            "b) Average speed method",
            "c) Spot speed method",
            "d) Elevated observation method"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Multiple linear regression method is used to determine the Passenger Car Unit (PCU). Average speed method, Spot speed method, and Elevated observation method are used to determine travel time and delay studies.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 166,
        "Question": "Which method represents the speed of a traffic stream as a function of the number of variables?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Modified Density Method",
            "b) Multiple linear regression method",
            "c) Headway method",
            "d) Chandra’s method"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The method that represents the speed of a traffic stream as a function of the number of variables is Multiple linear regression method. The PCU is calculated using the below formula,\nEn = Cn/C1,\nEn = PCU for a vehicle type n,\nCn = speed reduction coefficient for vehicle type n,\nC1 = speed reduction coefficient for passenger cars.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 167,
        "Question": "How many factors does Chandra’s method to determine PCU depends on?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 3",
            "c) 2",
            "d) 5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Chandra’s method used to determine PCU depends on 2 factors and they are the velocity of vehicle type and its projected rectangular area to calculate the PCU value.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 168,
        "Question": "Which of the following methods to determine PCU can only be applied in India?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Multiple linear regression method",
            "b) Chandra’s method",
            "c) Headway method",
            "d) Modified Density Method"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Chandra’s method is the only method to determine Passenger Car Unit (PCU) that can be applied to Indian heterogeneous roads. Other methods are suitable for developed countries having homogeneous traffic conditions.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 169,
        "Question": "Headway method is most suited on which terrain?",
        "Options": [
            "a) level terrain",
            "b) mountainous region",
            "c) hilly terrain",
            "d) desert"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Headway method is most suited to determine Passenger Car Units (PCUs) on level terrain. They are suitable when level of service (LOS) is low.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 170,
        "Question": "What are the normal time intervals for manual count?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5, 10 and 15 minutes",
            "b) 5, 10 and 20 minutes",
            "c) 10, 14 and 18 minutes",
            "d) 10, 15 and 20 minutes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It takes less than a day to complete manual counts for volume studies. The normal time intervals for manual count are standardly 5, 10 and 15 minutes. On Tuesday, Wednesday or Thursday counts are usually taken. Rush hours are avoided.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 171,
        "Question": "Most applications of manual count require ____",
        "Options": [
            "a) small samples of data",
            "b) large samples of data",
            "c) no data",
            "d) maximum data"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Most applications that use manual counts require small samples of data at a given section. Manual counts are occasionally used. They are used when an automatic count is not accessible.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 172,
        "Question": "The data obtained from volume counts helps to identify.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Speed of vehicles",
            "b) Critical flow time periods",
            "c) Design drawbacks",
            "d) Existing traffic signal drawbacks"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The data obtained from volume counts helps to identify Critical flow time periods. The impact of huge vehicles and pedestrians on vehicular traffic flow is also identified by the help of these information.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 173,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not determined by traffic volume studies?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Design criteria",
            "b) Vehicle classification",
            "c) Number of vehicles",
            "d) Movement of vehicles"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Design criteria is not determined by traffic volume studies. Vehicle classification, number of vehicles, and movement of vehicles are determined by this method.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 174,
        "Question": "What is the time interval at which automatic count is taken?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 hour",
            "b) 2 hour",
            "c) 1 week",
            "d) 1 day"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The time interval at which automatic count is taken is an hour for each 24 hrs period. It usually extends for a week, a month or even a year.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 175,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a method of recording automatic counts?",
        "Options": [
            "a) portable counters",
            "b) permanent counters",
            "c) videotape",
            "d) speedometer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Speedometer is nota method of recording automatic counts. Portable counters, permanent counters, and videotape are the methods by which automatic counts are recorded.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 176,
        "Question": "When demand exceeds the capacity of approach, the volume is counted as the vehicle _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) enters the intersection",
            "b) departs the intersection",
            "c) is in the middle of the intersection",
            "d) crosses an opposite vehicle in the intersection"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When demand exceeds the capacity of approach, the volume is counted as the vehicle enters the intersection. This is done so because these are a more precise reflection of demand.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 177,
        "Question": "How is “unstable queue buildup” identified at a un-signalized intersection?",
        "Options": [
            "a) queues that become smaller during each successive counting period",
            "b) queues that become larger during each successive counting period",
            "c) queues that remain the same during each successive counting period",
            "d) queues that increase exponentially during each successive counting period"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: “Unstable queue buildup” is identified at a un-signalized intersection by queues that become larger during each successive counting period. This happens when vehicles queued during a red interval are not thoroughly cleared.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 178,
        "Question": "Portable counters are generally used for _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Only major counts",
            "b) Only minor counts",
            "c) Both major and minor counts",
            "d) Not used for counting"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Portable counters are generally used for both major and minor counts. Major counts are made for a week each month for a year. While minor counts are made for one five day period in each season.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 179,
        "Question": "Which type of counter is used at mid-block locations?",
        "Options": [
            "a) permanent counters",
            "b) portable counters",
            "c) videotape",
            "d) audiotape"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation:  At mid-block locations, portable counters type of counter is used. They are not used at locations where the extent of coverage counts are very short. Locations at which sample counts are taken are called coverage counts.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 180,
        "Question": "As per IRC, for many days the traffic count should be taken for rural roads?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2",
            "b) 3",
            "c) 5",
            "d) 7"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: As per IRC (Indian Roads Congress), traffic count should be taken for 7 days for rural roads. The count should be taken for 24 hours in a day.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 181,
        "Question": "How many times should the traffic volume counts be taken in a year?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3",
            "b) 1",
            "c) 2",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Counts should be taken 2 times a year. One count should be taken during the peak season of harvesting and marketing an the other during the lean season. Counts should no the taken during abnormal traffic condition like a fair or exhibition.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 182,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a way by which traffic volume data is presented?",
        "Options": [
            "a) AADT",
            "b) Variation charts",
            "c) Traffic composition",
            "d) Modal average"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Modal average is a way by which spot speed data is presented. There are various processes by which traffic volume data is presented. AADT, Variation charts, and Traffic composition are some of them.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 183,
        "Question": "Which type of traffic volume presentation of data shows volume along various routes using bands proportional to traffic volume carried?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Traffic flow maps",
            "b) Intersection flow diagram",
            "c) Trend charts",
            "d) Traffic composition"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Traffic flow maps is the type of traffic volume presentation of data which shows volume along various roads using bands proportional to traffic volume carried.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 184,
        "Question": "Which of the following type of presentation of data is useful for future expansion, design, and regulation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Traffic composition",
            "b) Trend charts",
            "c) Traffic flow maps",
            "d) Intersection flow diagram"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Trend charts are the type of presentation of data which are useful for future expansion, design, and regulation. Trend charts show hourly, daily or monthly changes in the volume of an area.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 185,
        "Question": "What information does the Intersection flow diagram show?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Direction and volume of traffic at an intersection",
            "b) Direction and volume of traffic at a flyover",
            "c) Direction and volume of traffic at a oneway route",
            "d) Direction and volume of traffic at a two-lane highway"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Intersection flow diagram shows the direction and volume of traffic at an intersection. Traffic flow maps show traffic volumes on various routes while the trend charts show the change in volume of an area.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 186,
        "Question": "In Traffic flow maps, the thickness of lines represents ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Traffic volume",
            "b) Direction of flow",
            "c) Volume change",
            "d) Boundary for expansion"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In Traffic flow maps, the thickness of lines represents traffic volume. Traffic flow maps show volume along various roads using bands proportional to traffic volume carried.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 187,
        "Question": "What is thirtieth highest hourly volume?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hourly volume that is exceeded only 29 times a year",
            "b) Hourly volume that is exceeded only 30 times a year",
            "c) Monthly volume that is exceeded only 29 times a year",
            "d) Monthly volume that is exceeded only 30 times a year"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Thirtieth highest hourly volume is the hourly volume that is exceeded only 29 times a year. All other hourly volumes will be smaller than the thirtieth highest hourly volume. Facilities designed by this will be congested only 29 times a year.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 188,
        "Question": "What information does data from variation charts help to determine?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Peak traffic flow at various hours in a day",
            "b) Peak traffic flow at limited hours in a day",
            "c) Lowest traffic flow in a day",
            "d) Traffic flow at noon"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Variation charts help to determine peak traffic flow at various hours in a day. Variation charts provide the variation of flow hourly, daily, and seasonally. The amount of time necessary to change the colours of the traffic signal can also be adjusted using these charts.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 189,
        "Question": "Design of transportation facilities in urban transport infrastructural projects is based on which presentation of traffic volume data?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Variation charts",
            "b) Peak hour factor",
            "c) 30th highest hourly volume",
            "d) Trends charts"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Design of transportation facilities in urban transport infrastructural projects is based on Peak hour factor type of presentation of traffic volume data. It shows when the highest traffic flow occurs.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 190,
        "Question": "Which presentation of traffic volume data helps to plan transportation facilities for your future generations?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 30th highest hourly volume",
            "b) Variation charts",
            "c) Peak hour factor",
            "d) Trends charts"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Design based on the 30th highest hourly volume is economical. Highways are usually designed based on the 30th highest hourly volume. Though being economical it gives satisfactory results.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 191,
        "Question": "The average 24 hours volume at the given area over a year is known as _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) average annual daily traffic",
            "b) average daily traffic",
            "c) thirtieth highest hourly volume",
            "d) average annual weekday traffic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Average annual daily traffic (AADT) is the average 24 hours volume at the given area over a year. It is the total number of evictees crossing a section in a year divided by 365.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 192,
        "Question": "Why are traffic forecasts often does in terms of AADTs based on forecasting models?",
        "Options": [
            "a) AADTs are more stable than hourly volumes",
            "b) Hourly volumes are more stable than hourly volume",
            "c) AADTs are simple",
            "d) AADTs are economical"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Traffic forecasts often do in terms of AADTs based on forecasting models because AADTs are more stable than hourly volumes and hence their projections are more reliable.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 193,
        "Question": "What is Directional Design Hour Volume  (DDHV)?",
        "Options": [
            "a) AADTs converted to a peak-hour volume in the peak direction of flow",
            "b) ADTs converted to a peak-hour volume in the peak direction of flow",
            "c) Hourly volumes converted to a peak-hour volume in the peak direction of flow",
            "d) Weekly volumes converted to a peak-hour volume in the peak direction of flow"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Directional Design Hour Volume (DDHV) is AADTs converted to a peak-hour volume in the peak direction of flow. DDHV is found using the relationship,\nDDHV=AADTxKxD\nwhere,\nDDHV=Directional Design Hour Volume\nAADT=Average annual daily traffic\nK=proportion of daily traffic occurring during the peak hour\nD=proportion of peak hour traffic traveling in the peak direction of flow\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 194,
        "Question": "What does K factor represent in the relationship DDHV=AADTxKxD?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The proportion of AADT occurring during the 30th peak hour",
            "b) The proportion of ADT occurring during the 30th peak hour",
            "c) The proportion of hourly volume occurring during the 30th peak hour",
            "d) The proportion of weekly occurring during the 30th peak hour"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: K factor represent the proportion of AADT occurring during the 30th peak hour in the relationship DDHV=AADTxKxD. 30th peak hour is the hourly volume that is exceeded only 29 times a year.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 195,
        "Question": "K and D values from the relationship DDHV=AADTxKxD are based on which characteristics?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Local characteristics",
            "b) National characteristics",
            "c) Terrain characteristics",
            "d) Area characteristics"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The statement “K factor in the relationship DDHV=AADTxKxD increases with increasing development density” is false. The correct statement is “K factor in the relationship DDHV=AADTxKxD declines with increasing development density”. The traffic volume in high-density development area is greater than traffic volume in low-density area.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 196,
        "Question": "The average 24 hours volume at the given location for less than a year is called.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Average annual daily traffic",
            "b) Average daily traffic",
            "c) Thirtieth highest hourly volume",
            "d) Average annual weekday traffic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: K and D values from the relationship DDHV=AADTxKxD are based on Local characteristics. State highway departments monitor theses proportions and publish appropriate values in various areas in the state.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 197,
        "Question": "The D factor tends to be ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) more variable",
            "b) more stable",
            "c) less variable",
            "d) less stable"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Average daily traffic (ADT) is the average 24 hours volume at the given location for less than a year. It is collected for 6 months, a season, a month, a week, or 2 days.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 198,
        "Question": "How is planning analysis initiated?",
        "Options": [
            "a) With the conversion of AADT to DDHV",
            "b) With the conversion of ADT to DDHV",
            "c) With the conversion of hourly volume to DDHV",
            "d) With the conversion of weekly volume to DDHV"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement “Radial routes have higher D values than circumferential routes” is true. Radial routes have movements in an out of central cities while circumferential routes have movements going around areas of central cities.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 199,
        "Question": "The hourly volume that is exceeded only 29 times a year is known as _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) 30th highest hourly volume",
            "b) Peak hourly volume",
            "c) AADT",
            "d) ADT"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The hourly volume that is exceeded only 29 times a year is known as 30th highest hourly volume. 30th highest hourly volume also serves for design purposes. They are economical too.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 200,
        "Question": "What is directional volume?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Peak hour volume",
            "b) 30th highest hourly volume",
            "c) AADT",
            "d) ADT"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Directional volume is also known as Peak hour volume. Peak hour volume is the hour of the day that has the highest hourly volume. This traffic volume is used for design and operational purposes by engineers. Here each direction of flow is counted individually.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 201,
        "Question": "When are reversible lanes used?",
        "Options": [
            "a) When the directional imbalance is significant",
            "b) When the directional imbalance is insignificant",
            "c) When the traffic signal doesn’t work in one lane",
            "d) When there is a blockade"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Reversible lanes are used when the directional imbalance is significant. Reversible lanes are lanes in which vehicles may be driven in either direction, depending on the signal. Reversible lanes are used to enhance the flow of traffic in the time of rush hours.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 202,
        "Question": "What happens when recommendations of traffic impact studies that use the Design hourly volume (DHV) is implemented in the Peak hour warrant?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Congestion",
            "b) Installation of unwarranted traffic signals",
            "c) Economical design of highway",
            "d) Satisfactory design of highway"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement “Peak hourly volume is smaller than Design hourly volume” is true. Peak hourly volume (PHV) is 5-45 % lower than Design hourly volume (DHV).\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 203,
        "Question": "How is the design year determined?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Roadway network planning schedule",
            "b) City planning schedule",
            "c) National planning schedule",
            "d) International planning schedule"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: When recommendations of traffic impact studies that use the Design hourly volume (DHV) is implemented in Peak hour warrant installation of unwarranted traffic signals occurs. This increases traffic delays and stops and might even lead to accidents.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 204,
        "Question": "The maximum hourly traffic volume that a highway should be designed to serve without the level of service falling below a predetermined level is known as ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) AADT",
            "b) 30th highest hourly volume",
            "c) Design service volume",
            "d) Peak hour volume"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A design year is determined by a roadway network planning schedule. Roadway network planning schedules are 1, 6 or 20-year plans. Road improvements are done based on the traffic volume projected to a design year.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 205,
        "Question": "Why are Spot speed studies conducted?",
        "Options": [
            "a) To record the distribution of vehicle speeds",
            "b) To record the distribution of time taken to reach a destination",
            "c) To design signals",
            "d) To determine design speed"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Spot speed studies are conducted to document the distribution of vehicle speeds as they pass a cross-section of the highway. Spot speed is the instantaneous speed of a vehicle at a location.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 206,
        "Question": "On a freeway, spot speed studies are not conducted if the traffic volumes exceed _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) 700-1000 veh/hr/ln",
            "b) 500-600 veh/hr/ln",
            "c) 750-1000 veh/hr/ln",
            "d) 100-200 veh/hr/ln"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: On a freeway, spot speed studies are not conducted if the traffic volumes exceed 750-1000 veh/hr/ln. On an uninterrupted flow facility, the spot speed studies are not conducted if the traffic volumes exceed 500 veh/hr/ln.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 207,
        "Question": "The mean speed of all the vehicles crossing a location is known as ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Standard deviation",
            "b) Median",
            "c) Time mean speed",
            "d) Pace"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The mean speed of all the vehicles crossing a location is known as Time mean speed during the period of study. Time mean speed is the mean of instantaneous speeds. It helps to decide the distribution of speeds of vehicles.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 208,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a method to measure spot speed?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Long Base method",
            "b) Aerial Photography",
            "c) Inductive loop detector",
            "d) Weigh In Motion (WIM) sensor"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Long Base method is a method to measure spot speed. In the Long Base method, vehicles are timed over a long distance. The second method to measure spot speed is Short Base method. In the Short Base method, vehicles are timed over a short distance of about 2m.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 209,
        "Question": "What is the disadvantage of Direct Timing procedure?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Parallax effect",
            "b) Uneconomical",
            "c) Complicated",
            "d) Inaccurate results"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The disadvantage of Direct Timing procedure is the Parallax effect. Direct Timing procedure is the simplest procedure for Long base method. The reaction time of the observers is also a disadvantage here.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 210,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a procedure of Long base method?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Direct Timing procedure",
            "b) Enoscope",
            "c) Pressure contact tubes",
            "d) Radar speed meters"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Radar speed meters is not a procedure of Long base method. Direct Timing procedure, Enoscope, and Pressure contact tubes are the procedure of Long base method.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 211,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a disadvantage of Pressure contact tubes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Low initial cost",
            "b) Simple to install",
            "c) Easy maintenance",
            "d) Tubes are visible which affects the driver’s behaviour"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The disadvantage of Pressure contact tubes is that the tubes are visible which affects the driver’s behaviour. The rest of the options are the advantages of Pressure syntactic tubes.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 212,
        "Question": "Which of the following is an advantage of Enoscope?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Tubes are visible which affects the driver’s behaviour",
            "b) Parallax effect",
            "c) Inaccurate results",
            "d) Eliminates Parallax error"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The advantage of Enoscope is that it eliminates Parallax error. Enoscope is also inexpensive, simple, and easily installable. Enoscope is also called Mirror box. It is an L- shaped box with a mirror set at 45 degrees to the arms of the instrument.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 213,
        "Question": "Which of the following instrument works on the Doppler principle?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Enoscope",
            "b) Radar speed meter",
            "c) Pressure contact tubes",
            "d) Time lapse camera"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Radar speed meter is the instrument that works on the Doppler principle. Radar speed meters directly measure speed. It is installed near the edge of the carriageway at a height of 1m.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 214,
        "Question": "The average difference between observed speeds and time mean speed is _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) 85th percentile speed",
            "b) Median",
            "c) Standard deviation",
            "d) Pace"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The average difference between observed speeds and time mean speed is Standard deviation. 85th percentile speed is the speed beneath which 85% of the vehicles are driven. Median is the speed that equally divides the spot speed distribution.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 215,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an application of speed study?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Determining appropriate speed limits",
            "b) Analyzing the cause of accidents",
            "c) Deciding speed trends",
            "d) For deciding PCU"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Deciding PCU (Passenger Car Unit) is not an application of speed study. Determining appropriate speed limits, analyzing causes of accidents, and deciding speed trends are some of the applications of speed study.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 216,
        "Question": "Why are speed trends at local, state, and national level established?",
        "Options": [
            "a) To standardize a speed limit",
            "b) To compare the results",
            "c) To assess the effectiveness of the national strategies on speed limits",
            "d) For design purposes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The speed trends at local, state, and national level are established to check out the effectiveness of the national strategies on speed limits. They are also used to assess the effectiveness of enforcements.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 217,
        "Question": "With the help of speed studies, traffic operations are controlled and regulated to ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) establish safe speed limits",
            "b) analyze traffic capacity",
            "c) analyze the cause of accidents",
            "d) decide speed trends"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement, “Cost-benefit analysis of a highway project is an application of speed study” is true. A cost-benefit analysis is an assessment of the financial benefits and losses of various set of alternatives.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 218,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a way by which spot speed data is presented?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Average speed of vehicles",
            "b) Modal average",
            "c) Cumulative speed of vehicles",
            "d) Variation charts"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Variation charts is not a way by which spot speed data is presented. Variation charts are used for the presentation of traffic volume data. The Average speed of vehicles, modal average, and cumulative speed of vehicles are the way by which spot speed data is presented.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 219,
        "Question": "Which of the following way of presentation of spot speed data is a mathematical analysis?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Average speed of vehicles",
            "b) Modal average",
            "c) Cumulative speed of vehicles",
            "d) Variation charts"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The average speed of vehicles is the way of presentation of spot speed data which has a mathematical approach. In this analysis, arithmetic speed is taken as average speed.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 220,
        "Question": "The speed corresponding to the summit of the frequency distribution curve of spot speeds is _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Peak speed",
            "b) Ruling speed",
            "c) Modal speed",
            "d) Mean speed"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The speed corresponding to the summit of the frequency distribution curve of spot speeds is Modal speed. It is the speed at which largest number of vehicles travel.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 221,
        "Question": "What is the use of a cumulative speed distribution curve?",
        "Options": [
            "a) To determine the speed above or below which certain percentages of vehicles are moving",
            "b) To determine the traffic volume",
            "c) To determine the modal speed",
            "d) To determine the PCU"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Cumulative speed distribution curve is used to determine the speed above or below which certain percentages of vehicles are moving. This graph has the mean values of each speed group on the x-axis and the cumulative percentage on the y-axis.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 222,
        "Question": "Which of the following is considered to be the safe speed limit?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 98 percentile speed",
            "b) 85 percentile speed",
            "c) 50 percentile speed",
            "d) 10 percentile speed"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: 85 percentile speed is considered to be the safe speed limit. 85 percentile speed is the speed beneath which 85% of the vehicles are travelling at a point (15% of the vehicles exceed this speed at the point).\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 223,
        "Question": "Which of the following is considered to be the minimum speed limit on a highway?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 98 percentile speed",
            "b) 85 percentile speed",
            "c) 15 percentile speed",
            "d) 10 percentile speed"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: 15 percentile speed is considered to be the minimum speed limit on a highway. Speed less than this is generally prohibited since it leads to congestion and accidents.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 224,
        "Question": "98 percentile speed is _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) design speed",
            "b) safe speed",
            "c) minimum speed",
            "d) median speed"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: 98 percentile speed is design speed. It is the speed that is used for geometric design purposes. Median speed is the 50 percentile speed, safe speed is 85 percentile speed and the minimum speed is 15 percentile speed.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 225,
        "Question": "What is Modal speed?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Speed that is most likely to occur",
            "b) Speed that is least likely to occur",
            "c) Peak speed",
            "d) Minimum speed"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Modal speed is the speed that is most likely to occur. Modal speed is a measure of central tendency. It is a value of speed that occurs often in the sample of spot speed in the given data.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 226,
        "Question": "Which curve helps to determine Modal speed?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Frequency distribution curve",
            "b) Uniform distribution curve",
            "c) Normal distribution curve",
            "d) Poisson distribution curve"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Frequency distribution curve helps to determine Modal speed graphically. A vertical line is drawn from the crest of the curve and the modal speed is the value on horizontal axis of the graph.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 227,
        "Question": "What is Median speed?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Speed that divides the distribution in to equal parts",
            "b) Speed that divides the distribution in to unequal parts",
            "c) Speed that is most likely to occur",
            "d) Speed that is least likely to occur"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Speed that divides the distribution in to equal parts is known as median speed. This means that there are equal number of observations of speeds which are higher than the median as there are lower than the median.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 228,
        "Question": "Median speed is the 50th percentile speed in _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Frequency distribution curve",
            "b) Normal distribution curve",
            "c) Cumulative frequency curve",
            "d) Uniform distribution curve"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The statement, “Median speed is a negative value” is false. The accurate statement is, “Median speed is a positive value”. Median speed value is not affected by the absolute value of extreme observations\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 229,
        "Question": "How many primary traffic flow elements are there?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2",
            "b) 4",
            "c) 5",
            "d) 3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: There are 3 primary traffic flow elements. The inter-relationships between these elements aids in planning, designing, and assessing the benefits of implementing traffic engineering measures on a highway system.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 230,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an application of traffic flow theory?",
        "Options": [
            "a) to determine adequate lane lengths",
            "b) to study the interrelationships of traffic flow elements",
            "c) to determine PCU",
            "d) to determine the average delay at intersections and freeway ramp merging areas"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Determination of PCU is not an application of traffic flow theory. Determination of adequate lane lengths, study of the interrelationships of traffic flow elements, and estimation of delay at intersections are some of the applications of traffic flow theory.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 231,
        "Question": "Time-space diagram is a graph that describes the relationships between time of the vehicle as it progress in the highway and ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) green time",
            "b) location of intersections",
            "c) location of vehicles in a traffic stream",
            "d) density of traffic stream"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Time-space diagram is a graph that describes the relationships between time of the vehicle as it progresses in the highway and location of vehicles in a traffic stream. Time of the vehicle is on the x-axis and location of vehicles in a traffic stream is on the y-axis.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 232,
        "Question": "The number of vehicles travelling over a unit length of highway at an instant in time is ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) flow",
            "b) speed",
            "c) density",
            "d) acceleration"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The number of vehicles travelling over a unit length of highway at an instant in time is density. The unit of density is vehicle/m or vehicle/km. It is usually denoted by k.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 233,
        "Question": "The slope of time-space diagram is ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) flow",
            "b) speed",
            "c) density",
            "d) location"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The slope of time-space diagram is the speed of a vehicle at any time t. Speed is the distance travelled by the vehicle in unit time. It is expressed as km/hr or miles/hr. It is usually denoted by u.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 234,
        "Question": "The harmonic mean of the speeds of vehicles passing a point on a roadway during an interval of time is known as ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Density",
            "b) Flow",
            "c) Space mean speed",
            "d) Time mean speed"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Space mean speed is the harmonic mean of the speeds of vehicles passing a point on a roadway during an interval of time. It is the entire distance travelled by the vehicles divided by the total time required by these vehicles to travel that distance. Space mean speed is involved in flow-density relationships.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 235,
        "Question": "Flow can be determined by which for the following mathematical formula?",
        "Options": [
            "a) q = n x 3600/T",
            "b) q = n x 360/T",
            "c) q = T x 3600/n",
            "d) q = n x 60/T"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The statement, “The time-mean speed is always less than space-mean speed” is false. The correct statement is, “The time-mean speed is always higher than space-mean speed”. The difference between time-mean speed and space-mean speed tends to lessen as the absolute values of speeds increase.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 236,
        "Question": "What is the unit of time headway?",
        "Options": [
            "a) meter",
            "b) veh/m",
            "c) seconds",
            "d) m/veh"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Flow can be determined by the given mathematical formula, q = n x 3600/T. Here, q = flow in vehicle/hr, n = the number of vehicles passing a point in the roadway in T sec\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 237,
        "Question": "Which of the following equations shows the correct relationship between flow, density, and space mean speed?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Flow = density/space mean speed",
            "b) Flow = space mean speed /density",
            "c) Density = flow x space mean speed",
            "d) Flow = density x space mean speed"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Flow = density x space mean speed shows the correct relationship between flow, density, and space mean speed. It can also be written as q = kus.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 238,
        "Question": "On which of the following factors are flow, density, and space mean speed are not dependent?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Characteristics of the roadway",
            "b) Characteristics of the vehicle",
            "c) Topography",
            "d) Weather"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Flow, density, and space mean speed is not dependent on topography. They are dependent on characteristics of the roadway, characteristics of the vehicle, weather, and characteristics of the driver.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 239,
        "Question": "With respect to the shape of the flow-density curve, when the density reaches maximum the flow must be ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Maximum",
            "b) Infinite",
            "c) 0",
            "d) Minimum"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: With respect to the shape of the flow-density curve, when the density reaches maximum the flow must be 0. This is because vehicles tend to line up end to end. Maximum density is also known as jam density.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 240,
        "Question": "On which of the following factor does mean free speed depend on??",
        "Options": [
            "a) Physical characteristics of highway",
            "b) Characteristics of the roadway",
            "c) Characteristics of the vehicle",
            "d) Characteristics of the driver"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Mean free speed depends on the physical characteristics of the road. Mean free speed is the absolute maximum speed that is acquired when flow tends to zero. As the flow increases the speed decreases.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 241,
        "Question": "The macroscopic approach considers which of the following factor?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Spacing",
            "b) Speed",
            "c) Flow-density relationship",
            "d) Design"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Macroscopic approach considers flow-density relationship for describing traffic flow. It examines traffic streams and develops algorithms that describe the flow to the density and space mean speeds.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 242,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a model that is commonly used by the macroscopic approach?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Macroscopic Simulation Models",
            "b) Mesoscopic Simulation Models",
            "c) Greenshields model",
            "d) Travel Demand Models"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Greenshields model is a model that is commonly used by the macroscopic approach. Greenshields model hypothesized that there is a linear connection between speed and density.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 243,
        "Question": "Greenberg model uses which analogy?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fluid flow",
            "b) Laws of motion",
            "c) Secchi disk",
            "d) Turbidity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Greenberg model uses fluid flow analogy to develop macroscopic relationships for traffic flow. It is expressed in the following form, us = c ln(kj/k).\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 244,
        "Question": "The Greenberg model is used for which type of traffic condition?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dense",
            "b) Light",
            "c) Uncongested",
            "d) Unrestricted"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Greenberg model is used for dense traffic condition. The Greenberg model satisfies the boundary conditions when the density is proceeding towards the jam density. It does not satisfy the boundary conditions when density is proceeding towards zero.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 245,
        "Question": "When does the Greenshields model satisfy the boundary condition?",
        "Options": [
            "a) When the density is approaching zero as well as when the density is approaching the jam density kj",
            "b) When the density is approaching infinity as well as when the density is approaching the jam density kj",
            "c) When the density is approaching zero as well as when the density is approaching infinity",
            "d) When the density is approaching zero as well as when the density is approaching the jam density kj"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Greenshields model satisfies the boundary condition when the density is approaching zero as well as when the density is approaching the jam density kj. It is therefore used for both light and dense traffic.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 246,
        "Question": "The Microscopic approach does not consider which of the following factor?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Spacing between vehicles",
            "b) Flow-density relationship",
            "c) Design",
            "d) Speed of vehicles"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The Microscopic approach does not consider Flow-density relationship for describing traffic flow. The Microscopic approach is also known as car-following theory.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 247,
        "Question": "Which of the following cannot be determined by the microscopic model?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Velocity",
            "b) PCU",
            "c) Flow",
            "d) Density"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: PCU (Passenger car unit) cannot be determined by the microscopic model. It is used to decide velocity, flow and density of a traffic stream when it is in a steady state.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 248,
        "Question": "What is gap acceptance?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Maximum gap required to finish lane changing safely",
            "b) Minimum major-stream headway during which a minor-street vehicle can make a manoeuvre",
            "c) Time interval between the arrival of two cars",
            "d) Minimum gap required to finish lane changing safely"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Gap acceptance is the minimum gap required to change the lane safely. It is the process by which a vehicle moves to an available gap. A gap acceptance model reports how a driver decides whether to accept or not.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 249,
        "Question": "Which of the following equation can be used to determine the expected number of adequate gaps that will take place at an unsignalized intersection or at the merging area of an expressway?",
        "Options": [
            "a) P(0) = P(h>0, h=0) = e—λt",
            "b) P(0) = P(h=0) = e—λt",
            "c) P(0) x P(h>0) = e—λt",
            "d) P(0) = P(h>0) = e—λt"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: P(0) = P(h>0, h=0) = e—λt is the equation that can be used to determine the expected number of adequate gaps that will take place at an unsignalized intersection or at the merging area of an expressway.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 250,
        "Question": "Which of the following is determined by gap acceptance?",
        "Options": [
            "a) To determine the delay of vehicles in minor streams aiming to merge onto major streams",
            "b) To determine the maximum gap required to finish lane changing safely",
            "c) To determine the minimum gap required to finish lane changing safely",
            "d) To determine minimum major-stream headway during which a minor-street vehicle can make a manoeuvre"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Gap acceptance determines the delay of vehicles in minor streams which are aiming to merge onto major streams. This depends on the distribution of the arrival of mainstream vehicles at the area of merge.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 251,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a parameter of traffic stream?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Density of traffic",
            "b) Flow of traffic",
            "c) Speed",
            "d) PCU"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: PCU is not a parameter of traffic stream. Density of traffic, flow of traffic and speed are the parameters of traffic stream. The traffic stream parameters can be macroscopic or microscopic.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 252,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the parameter of traffic stream that has microscopic characteristics?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Flow",
            "b) Density",
            "c) Speed",
            "d) Space headway"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Space headway is the parameter of the traffic stream that has microscopic characteristics. Flow, density of traffic and speed are the parameters of traffic stream that has macroscopic characteristics.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 253,
        "Question": "What is the definition of Highway Capacity?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The minimum traffic flow that can be accommodated in a highway facility in a given time period under existing roadway and control conditions",
            "b) The maximum traffic flow that can be accommodated in a highway facility in the future",
            "c) The minimum traffic flow that can be accommodated in a highway facility according to data from the previous year",
            "d) The maximum traffic flow that can be accommodated in a highway facility in a given time period under existing roadway and control conditions"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Highway Capacity is the maximum traffic flow that can be contained in a highway facility in a given time period under existing roadway and control conditions. It is the maximum flow under prevailing conditions of road and traffic control systems.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 254,
        "Question": "How many types of highway capacity was defined by Highway Capacity Manual (1950)?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2",
            "b) 5",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: There are 3 types of highway capacity defined by Highway Capacity Manual (1950). They are basic capacity, possible capacity, and practical capacity. Highway Capacity Manual was introduced by O.K Norman.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 255,
        "Question": "Which of the following capacity is considered as design capacity?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Basic capacity",
            "b) Possible capacity",
            "c) Practical capacity",
            "d) Traffic capacity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Practical capacity is considered as design capacity. Practical capacity is the highest number of vehicles that can cross a given point in the roadway in an hour when the traffic density does not cause any risk or unwanted delay.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 256,
        "Question": "Which of the following parameter is not dependent on highway capacity?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Class of highway",
            "b) Lane width",
            "c) Number of lanes",
            "d) Gauge width"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Gauge width is the parameter that is not dependent on highway capacity. Class of highway, lane width, number of lanes, and intersections are the parameters dependent on highway capacity. Development of traffic management measures, geometric elements, and traffic control devices can also be achieved with the aid of studies on highway capacity.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 257,
        "Question": "What is the capacity value for urban roads as per IRC for one-way traffic flow with two lanes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1500 PCU/hr",
            "b) 2400 PCU/hr",
            "c) 3600 PCU/hr",
            "d) 4000 PCU/hr"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The capacity value for urban roads as per IRC for one-way traffic flow with two-lane is 2400 PCU/hr. It is 1500 PCU/hr for two-way two-lane traffic flow and 3600 PCU/hr for one-way three-lane traffic flow.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 258,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a factor affecting traffic capacity?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lane width",
            "b) Lateral clearance",
            "c) Gradient",
            "d) Traffic control devices"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Traffic control devices is not a factor affecting traffic capacity. Roadway conditions such as lane width, lateral clearance, gradient, and shoulders affect traffic capacity. Traffic conditions such as number of traffic lanes, driver characteristics, types of vehicles on the road also affect traffic capacity.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 259,
        "Question": "Highway capacity is independent of _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) demand",
            "b) lane width",
            "c) geometric design",
            "d) traffic conditions"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Highway capacity is independent of demand. Capacity is the number of vehicles that the road can accommodate in its existing condition. It is independent of the number of vehicles demanding service.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 260,
        "Question": "What is maximum flow rate?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Worst 15 minutes of the peak hours",
            "b) Worst 10 minutes of peak hours",
            "c) Worst 30 minutes of the peak hours",
            "d) Worst 5 minutes of the peak hours"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: “Capacity is a probabilistic measure” is a correct statement. It varies with respect to location and time. It is generally obtained through field observations.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 261,
        "Question": "Capacity is measured as a reasonably expected value and not the maximum flow rate observed in the facility. Why?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Because capacity at a given location varies from day to day",
            "b) Because capacity at a given location doesn’t vary",
            "c) Because capacity at a given location varies from year to year",
            "d) Because capacity at a given location decreases simultaneously"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Maximum flow rate is the worst 15 minutes of the peak hours. Capacity is the maximum flow rate that the road facilities can bear in prevailing condition.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 262,
        "Question": "Which one of the following is an interrupted facility?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Traffic signal",
            "b) Stop sign",
            "c) Yield sign",
            "d) Basic freeway"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Basic freeway is an interrupted facility. Traffic signal, stop sign an yield sign are external devices which partially interrupts the flow. Some of the interrupted facilities are weaving sections, ramps, and unidirectional multilane highways.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 263,
        "Question": "Freeway has which magnitude as the measure of effectiveness?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Density",
            "b) Speed",
            "c) Capacity",
            "d) Delay"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Freeway has a density as the measure of effectiveness. Multi-lane and two-way highways have speed/delay as the measure of effectiveness.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 264,
        "Question": "What is a basic freeway segment?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The section between two ramps which is unaffected by weaving and diverging maneuvers",
            "b) The section between three ramps which is unaffected by weaving and diverging maneuvers",
            "c) The section between two ramps which is affected by weaving and diverging maneuvers",
            "d) The section between three ramps which is affected by weaving and diverging maneuvers"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Basic freeway segment is the section between two ramps which is unaffected by weaving and diverging maneuvers. The ramps are either entrance or exit. In a basic freeway, the traffic flow is steady.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 265,
        "Question": "In how many steps is the freeway capacity determined?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The freeway capacity determined in 3 steps and they are theoretical capacity, prevailing capacity, and level of service and design service rate.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 266,
        "Question": "Basic or theoretical capacity under ideal traffic and environmental conditions can be determined by the concept that the _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) flow rate equals time divided by time headway; time headway equals distance divided by speed",
            "b) flow rate equals time multiplied to time headway; time headway equals distance divided by speed",
            "c) flow rate equals time multiplied to time headway; time headway equals distance multiplied to speed",
            "d) flow rate equals time added to time headway; time headway equals distance divided by speed"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Basic or theoretical capacity under ideal traffic and environmental conditions can be determined by the concept that the flow rate equals time divided by time headway; time headway equals distance divided by speed.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 267,
        "Question": "How is basic capacity determined by prevailing capacity?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Repeated observation of maximum traffic flow under peak conditions",
            "b) Repeated observation of minimum traffic flow under peak conditions",
            "c) Repeated observation of minimum traffic flow under ideal conditions",
            "d) Repeated observation of maximum traffic flow under ideal conditions"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The basic capacity is determined by prevailing capacity by repeated observation of maximum traffic flow under ideal traffic and environmental conditions. The capacity of a segment of freeway working under no ideal conditions will have capacity less than the basic capacity.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 268,
        "Question": "Two-lane highways have which factor as the MoE (measure of effectiveness)?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Density",
            "b) Capacity",
            "c) PCU",
            "d) Speed/delay"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Two-lane highways have speed/delay as the MoE (measure of effectiveness). Multi-lane highways too have speed/delay as the MoE. Freeways have density as the MoE.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 269,
        "Question": "Two-lane highways are classified into how many classes for the purpose of analysis?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 3",
            "c) 2",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Two-lane highways are classified into 2 classes for the purpose of analysis. They are class-I and class-II. Class-I facilities mostly serve long-distance trips while class-II facilities mostly serve short-distance trips.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 270,
        "Question": "What is a major consideration in class-I highways?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Density",
            "b) Delay",
            "c) Speed",
            "d) Distance"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Speed is a major consideration in class-I highways. This is so because in class-I highways motorists are expected to travel at high speeds.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 271,
        "Question": "Which type of roads does class-I include?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Major inter-city roads",
            "b) Village roads",
            "c) Districts roads",
            "d) Streets"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Major inter-city roads are the type of roads that are included in class-I. This is so because the speeds are relatively higher in major inter-city roads.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 272,
        "Question": "In which class of two-lane highway does motorists not travel at high speeds?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Class I",
            "b) Class II",
            "c) Class III",
            "d) Class IV"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In class II of two-lane highway motorists do not travel at high speeds. This type of roads are generally access routes to class I facilities. They are not primary arterials.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 273,
        "Question": "Which class of two-lane highway serves as scenic or recreational routes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Class I",
            "b) Class II",
            "c) Class III",
            "d) Class IV"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Class II of two-lane highway serves as scenic or recreational routes. In these types of road, motorists do not travel at high speeds relatively. Speed is not a primary consideration in this roadway.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 274,
        "Question": "In which terms is LOS defined in class I highways?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Only percentage time spent following",
            "b) Only average travel time",
            "c) Percentage time spent following and average travel time",
            "d) PCU"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement, “Class II of two lane highway is a short trip” is a true statement. In these types of roadway, sightseeing plays an important role. They are the beginning or end portion of a longer trip.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 275,
        "Question": "In which terms is LOS defined in class II highways?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Only percentage time spent following",
            "b) Only average travel time",
            "c) Percentage time spent following and average travel time",
            "d) PCU"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: LOS is defined in terms of percentage time spent following and average travel time in class I highways. In class I facilities the speed is relatively higher.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 276,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a correction or adjustment required for multi-lane highways?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lane width",
            "b) Lateral clearance",
            "c) Median time",
            "d) Length of highway"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Length of highway adjustment is not a correction or adjustment that is required for multi-lane highways. The lane width, lateral clearance, median time, and excess points adjustments are required for multi-lane highways.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 277,
        "Question": "What is the free-flow speed (FFS) of a multilane highway?",
        "Options": [
            "a) FFS = BFFS-flw-flc-fm-fa",
            "b) FFS = BFFS+flw-flc-fm-fa",
            "c) FFS = BFFS-flw-flc-fm+fa",
            "d) FFS = BFFS-flw+flc-fm-fa"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The free-flow speed (FFS) of a multilane highway is FFS = BFFS-flw-flc-fm-fa. Here, FFS=free flow speed, BFFS=base FFS, flw=adjustment for lane width, flc= adjustment for lateral clearance, fm=adjustment for median type, and fa=adjustment for excess point.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 278,
        "Question": "How much does the FFS decrease when 10 foot lanes are used?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 6.6 mph",
            "b) 6 mph",
            "c) 10 mph",
            "d) 2 mph"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: FFS decrease by 6.6 mph when 10 foot lanes are used. This is referred from exhibit 21-4 (adjustment of lane width) of the Highway Capacity Manual.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 279,
        "Question": "Calculate flc (lateral clearance) for a 4 lane highway with milepost markers which are located 3 feet to the right of the travel lane?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 9",
            "b) 11",
            "c) 5",
            "d) 6"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Lateral clearance, flc = LCright + LCleft\n\t\t\t\t          = 6 + 3 = 9\nThe flc (lateral clearance) for a 4 lane highway with milepost markers which are located 3 feet to the right of the travel lane is 9 feet.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 280,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the factor that affects the flow on multilane highways?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Uncontrolled excess form roadside",
            "b) Right turns",
            "c) Controlled excess form roadside",
            "d) Traffic signals"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Uncontrolled excess form roadside is one of the factors affecting the flow on multilane highways. The other factor is the left turns taken by the motorists.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 281,
        "Question": "Equivalent flow rate is calculated by which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) vp = V/(PHF x N x fhv x fp)",
            "b) vp = V x (PHF x N x fhv x fp)",
            "c) vp = V/(PHF + N x fhv x fp)",
            "d) vp = V/(PHF x N + fhv x fp)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Equivalent flow rate is calculated using vp = V/(PHF x N x fhv x fp). Here, vp = equivalent flow rate, V = directional hourly volume, PHF = peak hour factor, N = number of lanes in one direction, fhv= heavy vehicle adjustment factor, and fp = driver population adjustment factor.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 282,
        "Question": "What is weaving capacity?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The maximum number of vehicles per hour that can cross a weaving section in a period of time",
            "b) The minimum number of vehicles per hour that can cross a weaving section in a period of time",
            "c) The maximum number of vehicles per day that can cross a weaving section in a period of time",
            "d) The minimum number of vehicles per day that can cross a weaving section in a period of time"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: “Vehicles which doesn’t change lanes in the weaving section causes inconvenience in traffic stream” is an incorrect statement. The correct statement is, “Vehicles which change lanes in the weaving section causes inconvenience in traffic stream”. Hence weaving sections become the bottleneck of the road system.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 283,
        "Question": "Weaving capacity is affected by which prime factor given below?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Length of weaving section",
            "b) Driver characteristics",
            "c) Traffic police",
            "d) Traffic control devices"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Weaving capacity is the maximum number of vehicles per hour that can cross a weaving section in a period of time. It is also defined as the no. of lane change operations within the given weaving section.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 284,
        "Question": "Higher capacity value occurs when free-flow speeds are ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Higher",
            "b) Low",
            "c) 30 kmph",
            "d) 60 kmph"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Weaving capacity is affected by the length of the weaving section. In Type A configurations (in Highway Capacity Manual, 2000) there appears to be a great sensitivity to length and Type B and C sections show little difference in the capacity of the section.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 285,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a limitation of a rotary?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rotaries are self-governing",
            "b) Rotaries require a large area",
            "c) Eliminates severe conflicts",
            "d) Accidents are less"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Rotaries require large area hence they are a costly affair in urban areas. The advantages of rotary is that they are self-governing, eliminates severe conflicts and accidents.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 286,
        "Question": "How many traffic operations are there in a rotary?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: There are 3 traffic operations in a rotary and they are diverging, merging and weaving. Diverging is a traffic operation when the vehicles moving in one direction parts into different directions according to their destinations. Merging is the opposite of diverging and weaving is a combination of both.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 287,
        "Question": "Which one of the following is the empirical formula to find the capacity of the weaving section?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Qw = (280w(1+e/w)(1-p/3))/(1+w/l)",
            "b) Qw = (280w(1+e/w)(1-p/3))/(1-w/l)",
            "c) Qw = (280w(1-e/w)(1-p/3))/(1+w/l)",
            "d) Qw = (280w(1+e/w)(1*p/3))/(1+w/l)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement, “The capacity of rotary is found out by the capacity of each weaving section” is true. The minimum of the capacity of all the weaving section is the capacity of rotary.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 288,
        "Question": "The capacity formula is valid only if the weaving width is between _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) 6 and 18 metres",
            "b) 1 and 10 metres",
            "c) 3 and 9 metres",
            "d) 4 and 14 metres"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Qw = (280w(1+e/w)(1-p/3))/(1+w/l) is the empirical formula to find the capacity of the weaving section. Here, Qw = capacity of weaving section, w = weaving width, l = length of weaving, p = proportion of weaving traffic to the non-weaving traffic.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 289,
        "Question": "What are the upper limit and the lower limit of the traffic volume for the installation of a traffic rotary?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3000 and 500 vehicles per hour",
            "b) 5000 and 500 vehicles per hour",
            "c) 6000 and 500 vehicles per hour",
            "d) 3000 and 1000 vehicles per hour"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The capacity formula is valid only if the weaving width is between 6 and 18 metres.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 290,
        "Question": "What does macroscopic stream models represent?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Change in behaviour of one parameter with respect to another",
            "b) The flow density",
            "c) The maximum passengers the vehicle can accommodate",
            "d) The characteristics of vehicles with respect to pedestrians"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The macroscopic stream models state how one parameter’s behavior changes according to another parameter in traffic flow. The most important relationship that this model caters to is the speed and density relation.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 291,
        "Question": "What type of relationship did Greenfield assume in the speed and density relationship?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Elliptical",
            "b) Linear",
            "c) Exponential",
            "d) Parabolic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The type of relationship Greenfield assumed in the speed and density relationship was a linear relationship. Speed of the vehicle tends to decline as the flow rates increases. Drivers slow down when there is higher density to maintain what they perceive to be safe operations.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 292,
        "Question": "Which of the following given options shows the correct relationship between speed and density according to Greenshield’s model?",
        "Options": [
            "a) v = vf + (vf/kj).k",
            "b) v = vf – (vf/kj).k",
            "c) v = vf / (vf/kj).k",
            "d) v = vf * (vf/kj).k"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: v = vf – (vf/kj).k is the correct relationship between speed and density according to Greenshield’s model. He assumed in his model that the speed and density have a linear relationship.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 293,
        "Question": "What is the shape of the relationship between flow and density according to Greenshield’s Model?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Linear",
            "b) Parabolic",
            "c) Elliptical",
            "d) Exponential"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The shape of the relationship between flow and density according to Greenshield’s Model is parabolic. The flow(q) is equal to mean speed(v) multiplied to density(k).\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 294,
        "Question": "According to Greenberg’s Logarithmic Model, what is the relation between speed and density?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Linear",
            "b) Logarithmic",
            "c) Parabolic",
            "d) Exponential"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: According to Greenberg’s Logarithmic Model, speed and density have a logarithmic relationship. The Greenberg’s Logarithmic Model can be derived analytically.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 295,
        "Question": "Which of the following given options shows the correct relationship between speed and density according to Greenberg’s Logarithmic Model?",
        "Options": [
            "a) v = vo ln(kj*k)",
            "b) v = vo ln(kj+k)",
            "c) v = vo ln(kj-k)",
            "d) v = vo ln(kj/k)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: v = vo ln(kj/k) is the correct relationship between speed and density according to Greenberg’s Logarithmic Model. Greenberg’s Logarithmic Model is a macroscopic stream model.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 296,
        "Question": "What is the main drawback of Greenberg’s Logarithmic Model?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Density tends to infinity, speed tends to zero",
            "b) Mean speed tends to zero, speed tends to infinity",
            "c) Density tends to zero, speed tends to infinity",
            "d) Flow tends to zero, speed tends to infinity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The main drawback of Greenberg’s Logarithmic Model is that the density tends to zero and the speed tends to infinity. This reveals the incapacity of the model to predict the speeds at lower densities.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 297,
        "Question": "According to Underwood’s Exponential Model, what is the relation between speed and density?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Linear",
            "b) Parabolic",
            "c) Elliptical",
            "d) Exponential"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: According to Underwood’s Exponential Model the relation between speed and density is exponential. This model was made to overcome the limitation of Greenberg’s Logarithmic model.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 298,
        "Question": "Which of the following given options shows the correct relationship between speed and density according to Underwood’s Exponential Model?",
        "Options": [
            "a) v = vf.e-k/ko",
            "b) v = vf/e-k/ko",
            "c) v = vf*e-k/ko",
            "d) v = vf+e-k/ko"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: v = vf.e-k/ko  is the correct relationship between speed and density according to Underwood’s Exponential Model. Underwood’s Exponential Model is a macroscopic stream model.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 299,
        "Question": "What is the drawback of Underwood’s Exponential Model?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cannot be used for predicting speeds at high densities",
            "b) Cannot be used for predicting speeds at low densities",
            "c) Cannot be used for predicting flow at high densities",
            "d) Cannot be used for predicting mean speed at high densities"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The drawback of Underwood’s Exponential Model is that it cannot be used for predicting speeds at high densities. This is because, in this model, speed becomes zero only when the density reaches infinity.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 300,
        "Question": "What is meant by time-in-queue delay?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Time between a vehicle joining the end of the queue at a signalized intersection and the time it crosses the intersection",
            "b) Delay during which the vehicles is at rest",
            "c) Delay caused due to resistance of other traffic",
            "d) Time between a vehicle joining the end of the queue at an unsignalized intersection and the time it crosses that intersection"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Time-in-queue delay is the time between a vehicle joining the end of the queue at a signalized intersection and the time it takes to cross the intersection. Stopped time delay is the delay during which the vehicles are at rest.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 301,
        "Question": "Why are the control delay caused?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Control devices",
            "b) Speedometer",
            "c) Traffic",
            "d) deceleration to and acceleration from a stop to stopped time delay"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Control devices like signals cause control delay or fixed delay. Control delay includes both approach delay and time-in-queue delay. Approach delay is caused due to deceleration to and acceleration from a stop to stopped time delay.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 302,
        "Question": "Which of the following travel time and delay studies doesn’t require a test vehicle?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Floating car technique",
            "b) Average speed technique",
            "c) Moving vehicle technique",
            "d) License plate observations"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: License plate observations is the travel time and delay study that doesn’t require a test vehicle. It is one of the most common method for calculating travel time and delay.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 303,
        "Question": "How is average delay time calculated in License plate method?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Average delay time = (Sum of all delay time) / (Number of matched license plates)",
            "b) Average delay time = (Sum of all delay time) x (Number of matched license plates)",
            "c) Average delay time = (Sum of all delay time) + (Number of matched license plates)",
            "d) Average delay time = (Sum of all delay time) – (Number of matched license plates)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Average delay time is calculated in License plate method by the relation given below, Average delay time = (Sum of all delay time) / (Number of matched license plates). While the delay time is calculated by, Delay time = Observed travel time – Free flow travel time.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 304,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an application of travel time and delay study?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Collection of rating data",
            "b) Problem location identification",
            "c) Economic analysis",
            "d) Determining relation between mean speed and flow"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Determining relation between mean speed and flow is not an application of travel time and delay study. Collection of rating data, problem location identification, economic analysis an model calibration are some of the applications of travel time and delay study.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 305,
        "Question": "In which test vehicle technique the test vehicle has to make a round trip on a test section?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Floating-car technique",
            "b) Average-speed technique",
            "c) Moving-vehicle technique",
            "d) License plate technique"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The statement, “The driver has to drive the test car above the average speed of the traffic in an average-speed technique” is an incorrect statement. The correct statement is, “The driver has to drive the test car at the average speed of the traffic in an average-speed technique.”\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 306,
        "Question": "The selection of test to be a test-vehicle based or not depends upon which of the following criteria?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Available personnel and equipment",
            "b) Driver’s choice",
            "c) Type of road",
            "d) Location of test"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In Moving-vehicle technique the test vehicle has to make a round trip on a test section from east to west direction. In Floating-car technique the test car attempts to pass as many vehicles as those that pass the test vehicle.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 307,
        "Question": "Floating car method is also known as _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) Average speed method",
            "b) Moving vehicle method",
            "c) License plate method",
            "d) Riding check method"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Floating car method is also known as Riding check method. In a floating car method, the driver floats with the traffic by passing as many vehicles as possible without compromising on safety.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 308,
        "Question": "Which of the following data is not recorded by the observers during a floating car method?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Number of vehicles overtaking the test vehicle",
            "b) Number of vehicles overtaken the test vehicle",
            "c) Number of vehicles travelling in the opposite direction",
            "d) Number of pedestrians"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: “Detailed observation is acquired from the floating car method” is a true statement. It records details concerning all phases of speed and delay which also includes location, duration, and cause of delay.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 309,
        "Question": "Which of the following a disadvantage of methods with test vehicles?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Data storage difficulties",
            "b) Low initial cost",
            "c) Consistent data collection",
            "d) Detailed data"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Number of pedestrians is not recorded by the observers during a floating car method. The number of vehicles overtaking the test vehicle, the number of vehicles overtaken the test vehicle, and number of vehicles travelling in the opposite direction are some of the observations recorded by the observers.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 310,
        "Question": "Which of the following formula gives the correct determination of the minimum number of test runs in a floating car method?",
        "Options": [
            "a) N=((tα χ σ)/d*2)",
            "b) N=((tα χ σ)/d*3)",
            "c) N=((tα / σ)/d*2)",
            "d) N=((tα + σ)/d*2)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The disadvantage of methods with test vehicles is the data storage difficulties due to advanced and detailed data collection techniques. Other disadvantages are regular quality checks due to human and electric sources errors.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 311,
        "Question": "What are the limit of acceptable error for traffic operations, economic evaluation, and trend analysis studies?",
        "Options": [
            "a) ±2.0 to ± 4.o mi/l",
            "b) ±3.0 to ± 4.o mi/l",
            "c) ±1.0 to ± 4.o mi/l",
            "d) ±0.0 to ± 4.o mi/l"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: N=((tα χ σ)/d*2) gives the correct determination of the minimum number of test runs in a floating car method. Here, N = number of sample size or minimum number of test runs, α = significance level, σ = standard deviation, d = limit of accepted error.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 312,
        "Question": "What is acceleration noise?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Degree of discomfort of driver due to acceleration and deceleration",
            "b) Degree of discomfort of driver due to pedestrians",
            "c) Degree of discomfort of driver due to control devices",
            "d) Degree of discomfort of driver due to inadequate spacing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The limit of acceptable error for traffic operations, economic evaluation, and trend analysis studies is ±2.0 to ± 4.o mi/l. The limit of acceptable error is expressed as ‘d’. It is ±3 to ± 5.o mi/l for Highway needs and planning studies.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 313,
        "Question": "The average journey time T in minutes in the direction of flow is calculated by.",
        "Options": [
            "a) T = tw – (ny/q)",
            "b) T = tw + (ny/q)",
            "c) T = tw x (ny/q)",
            "d) T = tw / (ny/q)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: “In floating car method, the travel time is taken as the mean time recorded during the repeated procedure” is a true statement. Multiple numbers of test runs are done to get almost accurate data and results.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 314,
        "Question": "The average volume in floating car method is calculated by.",
        "Options": [
            "a) q = (na+ny)/(ta+tw)",
            "b) q = (na-ny)/(ta+tw)",
            "c) q = (na+ny)/(ta-tw)",
            "d) q = (na+ny)x(ta+tw)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Acceleration noise is the degree of discomfort of driver due to acceleration and deceleration. It is calculated as the root mean square value of acceleration considering each second of operation one by one.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 315,
        "Question": "Floating car method is suitable for which type of road?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Multilane highways",
            "b) Village roads",
            "c) State highways",
            "d) 2 lane 2 way highways"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The average journey time T in minutes in the direction of flow is calculated by T = tw – (ny/q). Here, T = average journey time in minutes, tw = average journey time when test vehicle is travelling with the stream q.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 316,
        "Question": "When is inaccuracy most likely to occur in floating car method?",
        "Options": [
            "a) During periods of congested flow on multi-lane highways",
            "b) In village roads due to bad road conditions",
            "c) When there are lots of potholes",
            "d) During non-peak hours in city roads"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The average volume in floating car method is calculated by q = (na+ny)/(ta+tw). Here, tw = average journey time when test vehicle is travelling with the stream q, ta = average journey time when test vehicle is travelling against the stream q.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 317,
        "Question": "Fixed delay is caused by ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) control devices",
            "b) impedance of traffic",
            "c) when the vehicle is at rest",
            "d) overtaking"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Fixed delay is caused due to control devices. Control devices in the road are traffic signals. Delay caused due to impedance of traffic is known as an operational delay. And the delay caused due to vehicle at rest id known as a stopped-time delay.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 318,
        "Question": "Why control devices like traffic signals should not be overused?",
        "Options": [
            "a) To reduce fixed delay",
            "b) To reduce operational delay",
            "c) To reduce stopped-time delay",
            "d) To reduce excessive delay"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The control devices like traffic signals should not be overused to reduce fixed delay. Traffic signals should be installed where there is no form of control that would be beneficial in guaranteeing safety and efficiency at the intersection.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 319,
        "Question": "Fixed delay does not depend on which of the following factor?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Traffic volume",
            "b) Traffic signals",
            "c) Level crossing",
            "d) Markers"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The above statement, “Level crossing causes fixed delay” is true. Fixed delays are caused due to control devices like traffic signals also.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 320,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an objective of OD Studies?",
        "Options": [
            "a) To determine the amount of by passable traffic that enters a town and thus establishes the need for diversion",
            "b) To develop trip generation and trip distribution models",
            "c) To determine the potential of the present highway system and plan for new facilities",
            "d) To assess the pedestrian pattern"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: To assess the pedestrian pattern is an objective of OD Studies. To determine the amount of by passable traffic that enters a town and thus establishes the need for diversion, to develop trip generation and trip distribution models, and to determine the potential of the present highway system and plan for new facilities are some of the objectives of OD Studies.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 321,
        "Question": "What do you mean by trips?",
        "Options": [
            "a) One-way movement of a person from origin to destination",
            "b) Two-way movement of a person from origin to destination",
            "c) Continuous movement",
            "d) A movement that is more than 50 kms"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Trip is a one-way movement of a person form origin to destination i.e. from start to where the person is going. OD Studies are used to determine and analyse trips.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 322,
        "Question": "Trips are classified into how many categories?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2",
            "b) 3",
            "c) 4",
            "d) 5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Trips are classified into 3 categories and they are internal, external, and through. Internal trip is from one point on post to another point on post, external trip is from on-post to off-post or vice versa and through is from off-post to off-post.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 323,
        "Question": "Which one of the following is not a common application OD survey?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Weaving-area studies",
            "b) Freeway studies",
            "c) Major activity centre studies",
            "d) Traffic volume studies"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Weaving-area studies, freeway studies, and major activity centre studies are some of the applications of origin-destination studies. Traffic volume studies is not an application of OD studies.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 324,
        "Question": "Why are screen lines required?",
        "Options": [
            "a) To check the accuracy",
            "b) To divide different types of vehicles",
            "c) To divide different types of goods and passengers",
            "d) To divide areas into urban and rural"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The statement, “OD surveys are conducted to study the pattern of persons and goods in a specific area of study during a certain period of time” is true. They are also used to plan new facilities.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 325,
        "Question": "How many methods are used for the origin-destination study?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 6",
            "b) 1",
            "c) 5",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: There are 6 methods for conducting the origin-destination study. The data collected from these studies help to modify or plan the pattern of the road. It also helps to compare the current and future potential of the road.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 326,
        "Question": "Which among the following is an origin-destination study?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Licence plate mail-out method",
            "b) Traffic mass study",
            "c) Floating car method",
            "d) Average speed method"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Licence plate mail-out method is an origin-destination study by which data is collected to help develop trip generation and trip distribution models and to determine the potential of the present highway system and plan for new facilities.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 327,
        "Question": "In which of the following origin-destination study licence plate numbers of vehicles are recorded?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Licence plate mail-out method",
            "b) Roadside interview",
            "c) Phone survey",
            "d) Mail back postcard survey"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In Licence plate mail-out method of origin-destination study, licence plate numbers of vehicles are recorded on a selected roadway and the owner of the vehicle is traced and mail survey is sent to the owner.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 328,
        "Question": "How many methods can be used for obtaining licence plate number of the vehicles in Licence plate mail-out method of origin-destination study?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2",
            "b) 3",
            "c) 4",
            "d) 5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: There are 2 methods by which licence plate number of the vehicles can be obtained by Licence plate mail-out method of origin-destination study. Taking photo or video or manually recording the tag on the vehicle are the two methods of recording licence plate number of the vehicles.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 329,
        "Question": "Which among the four method is preferred for high volume highways?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Photo/video",
            "b) Manual recording",
            "c) Interview",
            "d) Questionnaire"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Taking a photo/video is usually preferred for high volume highways when study is carried out by Licence plate mail-out method. Manual recording is generally preferred for low and medium volume highways.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 330,
        "Question": "Which of the following method has no disruption to normal traffic flow?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Licence plate mail-out method",
            "b) Roadside interview",
            "c) Questionnaire",
            "d) Toll booths"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Licence plate mail-out method is the origin-destination study which has no disruption to normal traffic flow because this method does not require vehicles to be stopped during the survey. The surveyor takes a photograph or video and records it without interrupting the flow of traffic.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 331,
        "Question": "Which of the following origin-destination study requires directing vehicles to a designated interview area and asking a series of short questions?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Licence plate mail-out method",
            "b) Roadside interview",
            "c) Phone survey",
            "d) Mail back postcard survey"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Roadside interview is the origin-destination study which requires directing vehicles to an assigned interview area and asking a series of short questions. The interview is a standard questionnaire regarding the origin and destination of vehicle that the owner of the vehicle has to answer.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 332,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an advantage of Roadside interview method?",
        "Options": [
            "a) High response rate",
            "b) Good sampling control",
            "c) Broad geographic coverage",
            "d) No interruption to traffic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Roadside interview method disrupts the flow of traffic. Other than that it is a very productive technique since it has a high response rate, good sampling control, and broad geographic coverage.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 333,
        "Question": "Roadside interview method is widely used for _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Truck and auto trip collection",
            "b) Village roads",
            "c) National highways",
            "d) Mountainous roads"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Roadside interview method is widely used for truck and auto trip collection. This is because roadside interview method has a high response rate and good sampling control. This method provides complete information.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 334,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the primary disadvantage of Roadside interview method?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Traffic disruption",
            "b) Requires more manpower",
            "c) Skilled surveyors",
            "d) Huge set of data"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Traffic disruption is the primary disadvantage of Roadside interview method. This method requires more traffic control at the location of the survey. But this method provides complete information.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 335,
        "Question": "When is mail-back postcard surveys usually used?",
        "Options": [
            "a) When traffic volume is high",
            "b) When traffic volume is low",
            "c) When traffic is homogeneous",
            "d) When traffic is heterogeneous"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Mail-back postcard surveys is usually used when traffic volume is high. This method has less traffic disruption compared to Roadside interview method.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 336,
        "Question": "How is mail-back postcard surveys conducted?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Postcard with a brief questionnaire",
            "b) Via email",
            "c) Via post",
            "d) Postcard with an elaborate questionnaire"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Mail-back postcard surveys are usually conducted using a postcard with brief questionnaire. The postcard is distributed to motorists at rest stations or at signalised intersections.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 337,
        "Question": "Which of the following is an advantage of the mail-back postcard survey?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Less personnel required",
            "b) Skilled personnel required",
            "c) More personnel required",
            "d) High response rate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Mail-back postcard survey requires less personnel. In this method, the postcard is distributed quickly at rest stops or signalised intersections. It has less impact on traffic. This survey has a low response rate.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 338,
        "Question": "Phone surveys are usually used for ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) household travel survey",
            "b) pedestrian survey",
            "c) traffic volume",
            "d) traffic flow"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Phone surveys are usually used for Household travel survey. This method has a higher response rate than mail-back postcard survey and lower response rate than the road interview method.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 339,
        "Question": "Which of the following method used cell phone tracking technology?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Phone surveys",
            "b) Mail-back postcard survey",
            "c) Road interview method",
            "d) GPS"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: GPS(Global Positioning System) uses cell phone tracking technology to determine origin-destination data for planning models. This method does not disrupt traffic and requires less personnel.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 340,
        "Question": "What are desire lines?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Illustrations on a map showing the flow of people or goods from point to another",
            "b) Illustrations on a map showing wind direction",
            "c) Separates two lanes",
            "d) Separates the soldiers from the lane"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Desire lines are illustrations on a map showing the flow of people or goods from point to another based on the values from a matrix. TransCAD Transportation Planning Software is used to illustrate desire lines.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 341,
        "Question": "Which one of the following is a disadvantage of a desire line?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The real distance and direction may be distorted",
            "b) Shows volume and direction of movement",
            "c) Can be superimposed onto a base",
            "d) Width of lines proportional to value"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The disadvantage of a desire line is that the real distance and direction may get distorted in order to get a clear image. The advantages are that it shows volume and direction of movement, can be superimposed onto a base, and width of lines proportional to value.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 342,
        "Question": "Which of the following represents traffic volume from one key area to another in a desire line map?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dark line",
            "b) Circles",
            "c) Triangles",
            "d) Dots"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Dark line of varying widths represents traffic volume from one key area to another in a desire line map. The desire line map locates pictorially the major traffic routes.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 343,
        "Question": "Which of the following represents traffic volume from one key area to another in a route volume map?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Circles",
            "b) Bars",
            "c) Lines",
            "d) Dots"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Bars signifying volume superimposed on an actual road map is used to represent traffic volume from one key area to another in a route volume map. Route volume map is a graphical representation.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 344,
        "Question": "What are traffic analysis zones?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Study area divided into a number of small units",
            "b) Group of study areas",
            "c) Points of the study area",
            "d) Zones of maximum traffic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Traffic analysis zones (TAZ) are study areas divided into a number of small units also known as zones. The zone within the study area is known as internal zones.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 345,
        "Question": "What is a zone centroid?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Point at which all attributes and properties are concentrated",
            "b) Point at which traffic is maximum",
            "c) Point at which surveyor takes data",
            "d) Point at which study area changes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Zone centroid is the point at which all attributes and properties are concentrated. The centroids are connected by centroid connectors to the nearest road junction or rail station.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 346,
        "Question": "What is the assumption taken in case of zoning models?",
        "Options": [
            "a) All individuals have the same travel cost from the centroid to the nearest transport facility",
            "b) All individuals have different travel cost from the centroid to the nearest transport facility",
            "c) All zones have the same travel cost",
            "d) Models are assumed to have constant travel cost"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The assumption taken in case of zoning models is that all individuals have the same travel cost from the centroid to the nearest transport facility. That is considered to be average for that zone.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 347,
        "Question": "The intersection from outside is normally represented through ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) external zones",
            "b) internal zones",
            "c) zone centroid",
            "d) study centre"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The intersection from outside is normally represented through external zones. The external zones are defined by the catchment region of the major transport links feeding to the study area.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 348,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an aspect of data preparation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Data correction",
            "b) Data expansion",
            "c) Data validation",
            "d) Data dilation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Data correction, data expansion, and data validation are the three aspects of data preparation. The raw statistics collected in the survey needs to be processed before direct application in the model. So data preparation is an essential step.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 349,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a type of data correction in the data preparation process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Household size correction",
            "b) Socio-demographic correction",
            "c) Non-response correction",
            "d) Input correction"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Input correction is not a type of data correction in the data preparation process. Household size correction, socio-demographic correction, non-response correction, and non-reported trip correction are the types of data corrections in a data preparation process.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 350,
        "Question": "What information does parking surveys not provide?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Data regarding availability of parking space",
            "b) Data regarding the extent of its usage",
            "c) Data regarding parking demand",
            "d) Data regarding pedestrians path"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Parking surveys do not provide data regarding pedestrians path. Parking surveys provide information about the availability of parking space, extent of its usage, and parking demand.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 351,
        "Question": "Which of the following parking statistics is expressed by accumulation curve?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Parking accumulation",
            "b) Parking volume",
            "c) Parking load",
            "d) Parking turnover"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Parking accumulation is the parking statistics that is expressed by the accumulation curve. \tAccumulation curve is the graph attained by plotting the number of bays occupied with respect to time.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 352,
        "Question": "The area under accumulation curve is known as _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Parking load",
            "b) Parking accumulation",
            "c) Parking volume",
            "d) Parking turnover"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The area under accumulation curve is known as the Parking load. Parking load is also obtained by multiplying the number of vehicles occupying the parking area at each time interval with the time interval.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 353,
        "Question": "Parking turnover is expressed as _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) number of vehicles per bay per time duration",
            "b) vehicle hours",
            "c) accumulation curve",
            "d) turnover curve"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Parking turnover is expressed as number of vehicles per bay per time duration. Parking load is expressed as vehicle hours and the accumulation curve represents parking accumulation.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 354,
        "Question": "Which of the following parking statistics gives an aggregate measure of how effectively the parking space is utilized?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Parking index",
            "b) Parking load",
            "c) Parking accumulation",
            "d) Parking turnover"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Parking index is the parking statistics which gives an aggregate measure of how effectively the parking space is utilised. The parking index is also called occupancy/efficiency.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 355,
        "Question": "Parking index is defined as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) the ratio of the number of bays occupied in a time duration to the total space available",
            "b) ratio of total vehicle hours to the number of vehicles parked",
            "c) total number of vehicles parked at a given duration of time",
            "d) number of vehicles parked at a given instant of time"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Parking index is defined as the ratio of the number of bays occupied in a time span to the total space available. It can be found out by, Parking index = (Parking load/Parking capacity)x100.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 356,
        "Question": "Fixed period sampling of parking surveys is similar to which of the following surveys?",
        "Options": [
            "a) In-out survey",
            "b) License plate method",
            "c) Turnover Surveys",
            "d) Duration Surveys"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Fixed period sampling of parking surveys is similar to In-out survey. In this survey all vehicles are counted at the beginning of the survey and then again after a fixed time interval of 15 minutes to1 hour.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 357,
        "Question": "Parking duration and turn over is not obtained in which of the following survey?",
        "Options": [
            "a) In-out survey",
            "b) License plate method",
            "c) Turnover Surveys",
            "d) Cordon count"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In-out survey does not provide parking duration and turn over as data concerning the time duration for which a particular vehicle used that parking lot is not noted.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 358,
        "Question": "Which of the following survey method is the most labour intensive?",
        "Options": [
            "a) In-out survey",
            "b) License plate method",
            "c) Turnover Surveys",
            "d) Cordon count"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: License plate method is the most labour intensive survey in parking studies. In the In-out survey, labor required is very less. Only one person may be enough for this survey.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 359,
        "Question": "Which of the following surveys provide the most accurate data?",
        "Options": [
            "a) In-out survey",
            "b) License plate method",
            "c) Turnover Surveys",
            "d) Cordon count"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: License plate method provides the most accurate and practical data in parking studies. In this survey, every parking stall is monitored at a continuous interval of 15 minutes and the license plate number is recorded.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 360,
        "Question": "Parking accumulation is defined by _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) the number of vehicles parked at a given instant of time",
            "b) the total number of vehicles parked at a given duration of time",
            "c) ratio of total vehicle hours to the number of vehicles parked",
            "d) aggregate measure of how effectively the parking space is utilized"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Parking accumulation is defined by the number of vehicles parked at a given instant of time. Parking volume is the total number of vehicles parked at a given duration of time.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 361,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a type of on-street parking system?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Parallel parking",
            "b) Right-angle parking",
            "c) 30 degrees parking",
            "d) Metered parking"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Metered parking is not a type of on-street parking system. Parallel parking, right-angle parking, 30 degrees parking, 45 degrees parking, and 60 degrees parking are types of on-street parking system.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 362,
        "Question": "Which type of parking has areas exclusively allotted for parking at some distance away from the mainstream of traffic?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Off street parking",
            "b) Parallel parking",
            "c) 30 degrees parking",
            "d) Right-angle parking"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Off street parking is the type of parking which has areas exclusively allotted for parking at some distance away from the mainstream of traffic. They are usually operated by public agencies or private corporations.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 363,
        "Question": "What are the parking requirements for residential plot area from 500 to 1000 sq. m?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Minimum one-fourth of the open area",
            "b) Minimum one-fifth of the open area",
            "c) Minimum one-third of the open area",
            "d) Minimum one-sixth of the open area"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The parking requirements for residential plot area from 500 to 1000 sq. m is minimum one-fourth of the open area. Offices require at least one space for every 70 sq. m as a parking area.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 364,
        "Question": "The rate of use of a parking facility is known as _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) Parking turnover",
            "b) Parking index",
            "c) Parking load",
            "d) Parking accumulation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The rate of use of a parking facility is known as Parking turnover. It is determined by dividing the number of available parking spaces into the number of vehicles parked in those spaces in a time period.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 365,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a type of Off street parking?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Surface car park",
            "b) Multi-storey park",
            "c) Roof parks",
            "d) Parallel parking"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Parallel parking is not a type of Off street parking. It is type of on-street parking. Surface car park, multi-storey park, roof parks, and underground car parks are some of the Off street parking facilities.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 366,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an objective of accident studies?",
        "Options": [
            "a) To evaluate existing design",
            "b) To compute the financial losses incurred",
            "c) To study the root cause of accidents and propose corrective measures at potential location",
            "d) To collect data regarding parking demand"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: To collect data regarding parking demand is not an objective of accident studies. To evaluate existing design, to compute the financial losses incurred, to study the root cause of accidents and propose corrective measures at potential location are some of the objectives of accident studies.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 367,
        "Question": "What is the first step in the accident study?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Accident data collection",
            "b) Accident investigation",
            "c) Accident data analysis",
            "d) Accident reconstruction"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The first step in the accident study is accident data collection. This data collection is generally done by the police. Motorists accident reports are considered secondary data.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 368,
        "Question": "Which of the following information does not require an accident data collection report?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Identification of spots at which unusually high number of accident happen",
            "b) Development of a method that allows identification of risks before accidents occur",
            "c) Comprehensive functional assessment of critical accident location to identify the causes of accidents",
            "d) Development of parking areas"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Development of parking areas does not require accident data collection report. Identification of spots at which unusually high number of accident happen, development of a method that allows identification of risks before accidents occur, and comprehensive functional assessment of critical accident location to identify the causes of accidents are some of the information that requires accident data collection report.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 369,
        "Question": "The development of different statistical measures of various accident-related factors gives insight into which of the following factors?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Causes of accidents",
            "b) Location of points at which unusually high number of accident takes place",
            "c) Identification of hazards",
            "d) Driver profiles"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The development of different statistical measures of various accident-related factors gives insight into driver profiles. It also gives insight into general trends and common casual factors.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 370,
        "Question": "Which of the following parameters given below is not required in accident data collection?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Registration number",
            "b) Details of road geometry",
            "c) Financial losses suffered due to property damage",
            "d) Sight distance"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Sight distance is the parameter that is not required in an accident data collection report. Registration number, details of road geometry, and financial losses suffered due to property damage are some of the parameters that is required in an accident data collection report.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 371,
        "Question": "Which of the following are the methods of reporting in accident studies?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Motorist accident report",
            "b) Car accident report",
            "c) Road accident report",
            "d) Highway accident report"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A motorist accident report is a method required for reporting in an accident study. The motorist accident report is filed by the motorist involved in the accident. Another method, police accident report is also used for reporting.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 372,
        "Question": "A police accident report is filed by _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) attendant police officer",
            "b) motorist involved in the accident",
            "c) witnesses of the accident",
            "d) relatives of the motorists involved in the accident"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A police accident report is filed by an attendant police officer. This report includes fatal accidents that require emergency or hospital treatment or which have suffered massive property damage.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 373,
        "Question": "Which of the following procedure of accident data collection involves obtaining information such as measurement of skid marks?",
        "Options": [
            "a) At Scene-Investigation",
            "b) Reporting",
            "c) Technical Preparation",
            "d) Cause Analysis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: At Scene-Investigation is the procedure of accident data collection that involves obtaining information such as measurement of skid marks. It also gives information regarding the photograph of the final position of vehicles, the examination of the condition and functioning of traffic control devices, and examination of damage of vehicles.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 374,
        "Question": "In which procedure determination of critical and design speed for curves is done?",
        "Options": [
            "a) At Scene-Investigation",
            "b) Reporting",
            "c) Technical Preparation",
            "d) Cause Analysis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Technical Preparation is the procedure in which the determination of critical and design speed for curves is done. This procedure is required for planning and interpretation of the study. It also involves measurement of grades and sight distance.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 375,
        "Question": "In which of the following procedure accident reconstruction is involved?",
        "Options": [
            "a) At Scene-Investigation",
            "b) Reporting",
            "c) Technical Preparation",
            "d) Professional Reconstruction"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In professional reconstruction process accident reconstruction is involved. In this step, attempt is made to determine from the data available on how the accident occurs from the accessible data.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 376,
        "Question": "What is the purpose of Accident data analysis?",
        "Options": [
            "a) To find possible causes of accident-related to driver, vehicle, and roadway",
            "b) To evaluate existing design",
            "c) To compute the financial losses incurred",
            "d) To collect data regarding parking demand"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The purpose of Accident data analysis is to find possible causes of accident-related to driver, vehicle, and roadway. Accident analyses are made to develop information such as drivers, pedestrians, vehicle, and roadway.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 377,
        "Question": "Why is it important to compute accident rates?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Because it reflects accident involvement by type of highway",
            "b) Because it reflects accident involvement by type of drivers",
            "c) Because it reflects accident involvement by type of pedestrians",
            "d) Because it reflects accident involvement by type of design conditions"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It is important to compute accident rates because it reflects accident involvement by type of highway. These rates compare the safety of different highway and street systems and traffic controls.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 378,
        "Question": "Which step in the accident investigation helps to determine how the accident occurs?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Professional Reconstruction",
            "b) At Scene-Investigation",
            "c) Technical Preparation",
            "d) Cause Analysis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Professional Reconstruction is the step in the accident investigation that helps us to determine how the accident occurs from the available data. It is also referred to as determining behavioural or causes of accident.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 379,
        "Question": "Analysis of accident reconstruction studies is done by which of the following step in the accident investigation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Professional Reconstruction",
            "b) At Scene-Investigation",
            "c) Technical Preparation",
            "d) Cause Analysis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Analysis of accident reconstruction studies is done by Cause Analysis. It is done to determine why the accident occurred from the data available.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 380,
        "Question": "The total accident hazard is expressed as ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) accident Rate per Kilometer",
            "b) accident involvement Rate",
            "c) death rate based on population",
            "d) death rate based on registration"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The total accident hazard is expressed as Accident Rate per Kilometer. It is the number of accidents of all types per km of a highway and street classification.\nR=A/L, where, R = total accident rate per km for a year, A = total number of accident occurring in one year, L = length of control section in kms\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 381,
        "Question": "Numbers of drivers of vehicles with specific characteristics who were participants in accidents per 100 million vehicle-kms of travel is known as ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Accident Rate per Kilometer",
            "b) Accident involvement Rate",
            "c) Death rate based on population",
            "d) Death rate based on registration"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Numbers of drivers of vehicles with specific characteristics who were participants in accidents per 100 million vehicle-kms of travel is known as Accident involvement Rate. Accident involvement Rate, R = N x 100000000/V here, R = accident per 100 million vehicle-kms of travel, N = total number of drivers involved in accidents and V = vehicle-kms of travel on road section during the period of investigation\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 382,
        "Question": "The traffic hazard to life in a community is expressed as _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) accident Rate per Kilometer",
            "b) accident involvement Rate",
            "c) death rate based on population",
            "d) death rate based on registration"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The traffic hazard to life in a community is expressed as Death rate based on population. Death rate based on population of the number of traffic fatalities per 100,000 populations.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 383,
        "Question": "Which rate reflects the accident exposure for an entire area?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Death rate based on population",
            "b) Accident Rate per Kilometer",
            "c) Accident Rate based on vehicle-kms of travel",
            "d) Accident involvement Rate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The rate which reflects the accident exposure for an entire area is Death rate based on population. It is the traffic hazard to life in a community.\nR = B x 100000/P, here, R = death rate per 100,000 population, B = total number of traffic death in one year and P = population of area\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 384,
        "Question": "The rate which reflects the accident exposure for the entire area and is similar to death rate based on population is _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) death rate based on population",
            "b) death rate based on registration",
            "c) accident Rate based on vehicle-kms of travel",
            "d) accident involvement Rate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The rate that reflects the accident exposure for the entire area and is similar to death rate based on population is Death rate based on registration.\nR = B x 10000/M, here, R = death rate per 10,000 vehicles registered, B = total number of deaths in traffic in a year and M = number of motor vehicles listed in the area.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 385,
        "Question": "The accident hazard is expressed as ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) death rate based on population",
            "b) death rate based on registration",
            "c) accident Rate based on vehicle-kms of travel",
            "d) accident involvement Rate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The accident hazard is expressed as Accident Rate based on vehicle-kms of travel. The Accident Rate based on vehicle-kms of travel is the number of accidents per 100 million vehicle km of travel.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 386,
        "Question": "Accident reconstruction helps in ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) controlling or imposing rules to control or check movement of vehicles on road at high speed",
            "b) to organize and interpret the study",
            "c) to determine why the accident occurred",
            "d) obtain information at the scene"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation:  Accident reconstruction helps in controlling or imposing rules to control or inspect movement of vehicles on road at high speed. It deals with representing the accidents occurred in schematic diagram to determine the speed before the collision.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 387,
        "Question": "The data which is not required to determine the pre-collision speed is ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) mass of the vehicle",
            "b) velocities after collision",
            "c) path of a vehicle as it proceeds towards collision point",
            "d) road width"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Road width is not required to determine the pre-collision speed. Mass of the vehicle, velocities after the collision, and path of each vehicle as it approaches collision point are the datas required to determine the pre-collision speed.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 388,
        "Question": "What is a collision diagram?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Schematic diagram of the collision of two vehicles that occur during turning movements",
            "b) Schematic graph of collision of two vehicles",
            "c) Schematic diagram of collision of three vehicles occur during turning movements",
            "d) Schematic graph of collision at turning movements"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A collision diagram is the schematic diagram of the collision of two vehicles that occur during turning movements. A collision is represented by a set of arrows to show the orientation of before and after movement.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 389,
        "Question": "Poisson impact theory divides impact into how many parts?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2",
            "b) 3",
            "c) 4",
            "d) 5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Poisson impact theory divides impact into 2 parts and they are compression and restitution. The compression phase in this theory is cited by the deformation of the cars. It follows Newton’s law F = ma.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 390,
        "Question": "What is an angular collision?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Collision when two vehicles coming at right angles collides with each other and bifurcates in a different direction",
            "b) Collision when two vehicles coming at 60 degrees angles collides with each other and bifurcates in a different direction",
            "c) Collision when two vehicles coming at 30 degrees angles collides with each other and bifurcates in a different direction",
            "d) Collision when two vehicles coming at 180 degrees angles collides with each other and bifurcates in a different direction"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Angular collision is a type of collision when two vehicles coming at right angles collides with each other and bifurcates in a different direction. The diagram consists of an outline map showing the direction of movement of vehicles and pedestrians involved in accidents.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 391,
        "Question": "The direction of vehicles after an angular collision depends on ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) initial speeds of the two vehicles and their weights",
            "b) final speeds of the two vehicles and their weights",
            "c) the angle at which they collide",
            "d) the type of vehicle"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The direction of vehicles after an angular collision depends on the initial speeds of the two vehicles and their weights. Collision diagrams are used to identify similar accident patterns.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 392,
        "Question": "What is a collision diagram?",
        "Options": [
            "a) A schematic diagram of collision of two vehicles that occur during turning movements",
            "b) collision when two vehicles coming at right angles collides with each other and bifurcates in a different direction",
            "c) A schematic diagram of collision of more than two vehicles",
            "d) A schematic diagram of collision of two vehicles that occur after turning movements"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A collision diagram is a schematic diagram of collision of two vehicles that occur during turning movements. In a collision diagram, each collision is symbolized by a set of arrows to indicate the direction.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 393,
        "Question": "Which of the following is one of the uses of a collision diagram?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Record of accident occurrence",
            "b) Redesign of traffic lights",
            "c) Demarcating area for parking",
            "d) Interpreting traffic data"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A collision diagram is useful for the study and analysis of a specific intersection or curve at which a multiple numbers of accidents have occurred. It gives the record of accident occurrence in an area.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 394,
        "Question": "Inadequate shoulder on a road can result in which type of accident?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Overturn",
            "b) Fixed object",
            "c) Right-angle",
            "d) Rear-end"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Inadequate shoulder on a road can result in an overturn. Other possible causes can be roadside or pavement features. Flattening slopes and ditches and relocating drainage facilities can help be done to avoid these types of accidents.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 395,
        "Question": "Inadequate lighting and Inadequate pavement marking can result in which type of accident?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Overturn",
            "b) Fixed object",
            "c) Right-angle",
            "d) Rear-end"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Inadequate lighting and Inadequate pavement marking can result in a Fixed object type of accident. This kind of accidents can be avoided by providing adequate lighting and installing reflectorized pavement lines or raised markers.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 396,
        "Question": "Restricted sight distance and large total intersection volume can result in which type of accident?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Overturn",
            "b) Fixed object",
            "c) Right-angle",
            "d) Rear-end"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Restricted sight distance and large total intersection volume can result in Right-angle collisions at unsignalized intersections. These accidents can be avoided by installing signals and restricting parking near corners.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 397,
        "Question": "Accidents due to high approach speed can be fixed by _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) installing rumble strips",
            "b) restricting parking near corners",
            "c) installing reflectorized pavement lines",
            "d) installing stop signs"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Accidents due to high approach speed can be fixed by installing rumble strips. High approach speed also leads to Right-angle collisions at unsignalized intersections.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 398,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the possible cause of rear end collision at unsignalised intersections?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pedestrian crossing",
            "b) High approach speed",
            "c) Restricted sight distance",
            "d) Poor visibility"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The possible cause of rear-end collision at unsignalised intersections is pedestrian crossing. It can be avoided by installing warning signs and signing or marking of pedestrians crosswalks.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 399,
        "Question": "Accidents due to inadequate channelisation can be fixed by _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) providing turning bays",
            "b) restricting parking near corners",
            "c) installing reflectorized pavement lines",
            "d) installing stop signs"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Accidents due to inadequate channelisation can be fixed by providing turning bays. It can be corrected by providing turning bays, improving channelisation and installing acceleration and deceleration lanes.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 400,
        "Question": "Inadequate barrier systems in bridges can lead to an accident. It can be avoided by which of the following safety measure?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Remove hazardous curb",
            "b) Resurface decks",
            "c) Installing signals",
            "d) Installing reflectorized pavement lines"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Accident due to Inadequate barrier system in bridges can be avoided by removing hazardous curb. Upgrading bridge rail, upgrading approach rails and improving delineation are some of the safety measures that can also be followed.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 401,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the possible cause of pedestrian/bicycle accidents?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Limited sight distance",
            "b) Inadequate barrier system",
            "c) Inadequate channelisation",
            "d) Large total intersection volume"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Limited sight distance is the possible cause of pedestrian/bicycle accidents. Inadequate signals and protection are some of the causes of pedestrian/bicycle accidents. By removing sight obstruction this kind of accidents can be avoided.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 402,
        "Question": "Poor delineation and poor visibility lead to which type of accidents?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Run-off-road",
            "b) Fixed object",
            "c) Right-angle",
            "d) Rear-end"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Poor delineation and poor visibility lead Run-off-road accident. This accident can be avoided by installing road delineators, installing warning signs, improving road lighting and installing pavement markings.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 403,
        "Question": "Inadequate road design or maintenance leads to which type of accident?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sideswipe",
            "b) Run-off-road",
            "c) Fixed object",
            "d) Right-angle"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Inadequate road design or maintenance leads to Sideswipe or head-on accidents. This type of accident can be avoided by providing wider lanes, providing passing lanes and providing roadside delineators.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 404,
        "Question": "Rough crossing angle and sharp angle crossing are the causes of which type of accident?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Collision at railroad crossing",
            "b) Sideswipe",
            "c) Run-off-road",
            "d) Fixed object"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Rough crossing angle and sharp angle crossing cause collision at railroad crossing. This type of accident can be avoided by improving the crossing surface and rebuilding crossing with proper angle.\n"
    }
]